<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The London jilt, or, The Politick whore. The second and last part shewing all the artifices and stratagems which the ladies of pleasure make use of for the intreaguing and decoying of men interwoven with several pleasant stories of the misses ingenious performances.</title>
            <author>Oldys, Alexander.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1683</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 158 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 67 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A49085</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L2897C</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R37996</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">17160437</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 17160437</idno>
            <idno type="VID">106022</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A49085)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 106022)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1619:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The London jilt, or, The Politick whore. The second and last part shewing all the artifices and stratagems which the ladies of pleasure make use of for the intreaguing and decoying of men interwoven with several pleasant stories of the misses ingenious performances.</title>
                  <author>Oldys, Alexander.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 127 p., [1] leaf of plates : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Hen. Rhodes ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1683.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Alexander Oldys by NUC pre-1956 imprints.</note>
                  <note>Contains engraved frontispiece.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:106022:1"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>image of devils grabbing a woman</figDesc>
                  <head>THE POLITICK WHORE The ſecond and last part.</head>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:106022:1"/>
            <p>THE <hi>LONDON JILT:</hi> OR, THE POLITICK WHORE.</p>
            <p>The Second and Laſt Part.</p>
            <p>SHEWING, All the Artifices and Stra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagems which the Ladies of Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure make uſe of for the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treaguing and Decoying of Men; Interwoven with ſeveral Pleaſant Stories of the <hi>Miſſes</hi> Ingenious Performances.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Hen. Rhodes,</hi> next door to the <hi>Bear-Tavern</hi> near <hi>Bride-lane</hi> in <hi>Fleet-ſtreet.</hi> 1683.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:106022:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:106022:2"/>
            <head>THE <hi>LONDON JILT:</hi> OR, THE POLITICK WHORE.</head>
            <head type="sub">The Second and Laſt Part.</head>
            <p>AFTER that I had thus deceiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the <hi>Hop Merchant,</hi> and had removed with my Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous Mother into an other Lodging, a certain Sparke who for his Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney enjoyed my Favours, brought an other with him, when that we had dewlt there about ſeven or eight Months, who was a Widdower, and drove a great Trade in To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bacco. This Man was about 23 or 24 Years old, but in a little time I obſerved by
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:106022:3"/>his Diſcourſe, that he was a Man of great experience in things that had any Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity with my way of living, as alſo in all the Circumſtances, that are proper for the gaining a Woman's heart, and more Capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city could not have been expected in a Man of three times his Age; he being ſtill ſo young, I was amazed that he uſed his Wife at that rate, as to diſpatch her ſo ſoon, and I began to rally him upon the buſineſs, but he had his Anſwer ſo ready, that I might ſay, I had found the Man I wanted. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt ſeveral other Diſcourſes that he held me, <hi>Without doubt</hi> (ſaid he to me with a ſmiling Countenance) <hi>after having been mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried only five or ſix Months, Death would not have deprived me of an ungly Wife, when I only Married for the ſake of her Riches, than to furniſh me with the Convenience of chooſing another adorn'd with ſo many Graces and Charms as your ſelf.</hi> I took little notice of theſe Words, becauſe I thought they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded more from meer Civility, than from a Heart truly ſincere. However I could well enough bear with 'em coming from his Mouth, and liſten to 'em, both for that he was a handſom Man and very advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geouſly rich, as I was aſſured by him that brought him to me, ſo that there was a Pleaſure in hearing one's Praiſes from ſuch
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:106022:3"/>a Perſon: and for my part I was very well ſatisfyed with him, which made me ſhow him a much more Familiar and Amiable Countenance, than I was uſed to do to any other in a firſt Viſit; for certainly though Women may ſhow themſelves ſomething Diſdainful and Coy, when Men exalt their Beauties in their Preſence, and though they make a ſhow of giving no ear thereto, yet I proteſt there is nothing they believe more eaſily. Wherefore the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Proverb ſays very patt, and to the Purpoſe, <hi>Tell a Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man but once ſhee's handſom, and the Devil will tell it her a thouſand times afterwards:</hi> And this is very true, for thoſe Words run ſo much in their Heads, that it often breaks their Reſt, and even there is not one how ugly and miſhaped ſoever ſhe may be, but taxes the Republick of <hi>Venice,</hi> of having u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed falſification in regard of her Glaſs, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than believe that ſhe is wholly ſo as Nature, and the Courſe of Years have made her, ſuch a ſtrong fancy have theſe poor Creatures that Beauty is an inſeparable Propriety of the Female Sex.</p>
            <p>In a few days after, this Tobacco Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant came to viſit me again, and beſides, that being ſo well made of his Perſon, he could not but be agreeable, he had ſuch Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant Diſcourſes, and he knew in a ſhort time
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:106022:4"/>ſo well to inſinuate himſelf into my favour, that one Night I graced him with half of my Bed, with a firm Confidence that he knew how to move the reſt of his Body as dextrouſly as his Tongue; and truly I was not at all deceived herein, for he was ſo great a Maſter in that Profeſſion, that <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rora</hi> ſooner approach'd than I could have wiſh'd it, and found us lying and panting in one anothers Arms.</p>
            <p>This cauſed a great Amazement in my Mother, for I had not yet received from that Lover any Benefit of any great Impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance; whereas otherwiſe I never permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted any one ſhould obtain the leaſt Courteſy from me, till after having frequented me a long time, and that I had drawn from them as much Money, as I could imagine to have an Obligation to them; but one of the three Torments, which torment the Minds of Mortals, now by the Fleſh had ſo unmercifully diſquieted me ſince the firſt time I ſaw him, that in the Night I could hardly hold my Legs ſtill, when the Thoughts I had had in the Day-time came to renew themſelves in my head, ſo great is the Power of a Man in the Heart of a Woman, when his Tongue is well hung and he is handſom of Perſon, and when they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to maintain together a particular Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſtion,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:106022:4"/>and that one finds that theſe Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties ought not to yield to one another. I certifie to you according to the experience I have had thereof, and all Women who have ſo open and frank a Heart as mine, will confeſs as well as I do, that there is nothing under the Sun that has ſuch pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erful Attractions, and that the Load-ſtone cannot have more Virtue to draw Iron and Steel towards it, than thoſe Parts have to attract one another Reciprocally.</p>
            <p>We had for about ſix Months ſpent our time in this incomparable Divertiſement, without however my being in any manner obliged to abandon my other Lovers, who tickled my Toby, and paid me for it ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently (for my Tobacco Man who had not the Civility to honour me of his own Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, with any thing of value, and whom I never ſollicited to give me any thing, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I bore him too great a Love, and was afraid of loſing him) knew very well that I could not maintain my ſelf in my Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with wind, and he did not ſeem to be very much diſquieted upon this account, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided he might have perferably before any other, his Elbow-room with me. We had ſpent, I ſay, about ſo much time in this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, when that one Morning as we were in Bed in Love and Delight, he began to
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:106022:5"/>relate to me how he got acquainted with his firſt Wife, who had been old, ugly, and rich, and with whom he had made a conſiderable Fortune, after having given himſelf to all manner of Debauches during his Youth.</p>
            <p>This Relation having already laſted near half an hour without my comprehending what all theſe things tended to, he asked me after a ſerious manner, if I would abandon this Libertine and diſorderly way of Living, and if I could live contented with one Man who loved me from the very bottom of his Heart? I made him anſwer in the Affirmative, and that there was nothing I aſpired to with more diſquiet, unleſs that it would pleaſe Heaven to addreſs a good Man to me, which though I lived in that manner, was not all the ſame thing to me, but, that with ſuch a Man as he, I knew how to comport my ſelf ſo honourably and ſo virtuouſly, as the diſcreeteſt Woman in all the City of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> could do.</p>
            <p>And thereupon taking him about the Neck to kiſs him, I gave him a hundred Kiſſes, letting at the ſame time many Tears trickle down my Cheeks, as if it had been for a ſign of my Repentance, for the Life I had thitherto led; I knew beſides, ſo well how to play my part, by aſſuring him that
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:106022:5"/>the firſt cauſe that had conſtrained me there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, was Poverty, that his Heart began to be moved ſo far, as that I fancied I ſaw ſome Signs of Tears in his Eyes. I eaſily perceive (ſaid he) that I run a riſque to ruine my ſelf by loving you, and that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibly I ſhall fall again into my firſt Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, if I do not endeavour to make ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Proviſion againſt it, by ſome means which may help me, for it is abſolutely impoſſible for me to live much longer without you. Since then I muſt of neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity make choice of one of the two Evils, methinks that it is much better to Marry together betimes, than wait till Old Age, and perhaps Poverty comes. But (added he) be careful that I never find the leaſt In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidelity on your part, and be aſſured that I have padded this way long enough to know all the Turnings and Windings of it; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon he was going to make a conſiderable number of Threatnings, but I ſtopped his deſign by as many Vows, which I thought were neceſſary for the imprinting in him good Sentiments of my Perſon.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reader,</hi> do not overmuch wonder at the Folly of him who in a ſhort time after was my Husband, for there are ſo many Men who take Wives who have had to do with other Men for ſeveral Years before, that
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:106022:6"/>the City of <hi>London</hi> is able to furniſh above Fifty Thouſand of that ſort of Sparks: And pray you, why ſhould not thoſe poor Devils find Men as well as others, ſince it is moſt certain, that by a long experience they have rendred themſelves more capable of the buſineſs; and that beſides they ſpare thoſe poor Cullies the pains of employing ſo terrible a ſtrength to break the Fin of an affected Maydenhead? Certainly if you are not yet Marryed, you will think with your ſelf, that you would do your buſineſs bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. And in caſe there be here and there a Woman who has not given her ſelf up long to this Commerce, and who has not kept Company with many Perſons, yet you are not aſſured that ſhe who ſhall fall into your Arms, has never had to do with an other. For this is ſo common in the Age we live, that a certain Clerk of a Church declared to me, that in the time of ſix Years, dur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing which he had exerciſed that Charge, there had not been one Bride that had ſprinkled the Chancery with her Tears, which has in all times been an infallible ſign of a Maydenhead; and if you have not yet loſt that your ſelf, I would yet leſs ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe you to ſeek out one of that ſort, for two Perſons who are Novices and unexpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rienced in Copulation, the Children they
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:106022:6"/>get are commonly Fools, which is a thing People ought to be more careful of than any other.</p>
            <p>Some days after that we had held ſuch Diſcourſes together, we went to the Parſon to have him Ask us in the Church the <hi>Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day</hi> following; but it would be tedious to relate all the Particulars of thoſe Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, ſome Children as well as Men in Years are acquainted with all the Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of that matter. Thus I will only tell you, that after the Publication of our Banes, we went to <hi>Barnet</hi> and were Marry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed there, becauſe if my Dear Husband had kept his Wedding in the City, he would have ſeen too many Sons-in-Law.</p>
            <p>Thus as ſoon as we were engaged to one another conformably to the Ceremonies, and that I had removed my goods into a new Habitation; my Husband required of me that I would take a Room for my Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, becauſe he would in no wiſe conſent ſhe ſhould dwell with us, alledging for Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>text, that that was often an occaſion of Quarrels and Trouble amongſt young Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed People, by reaſon that commonly young Women depend a little too much on their Parents, which hinders them from acknowledging the Soveraignty of their Husband, and from rendring them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:106022:7"/>ſubject to the Laws of Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</p>
            <p>As I was very much uſed to my Mother's Company, I imagined at firſt he did me a great injury, but afterwards having taken all things into ſerious Conſideration, I was overjoyed to find him ſo reſolved; for tho' I had not yet any deſign of committing to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards him any Act of Infidelity, by reaſon, that to ſpeak the truth, I loved him from the bottom of my Heart, yet I knew very well that there might be ſuch Occaſions of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered as might make us change our Senti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and that in ſuch a caſe it is better to truſt to Parents than to Strangers; which is beyond all Diſpute.</p>
            <p>Thus I took two Rooms for the poor Woman; but I charged her to ſpeak but of one to my Husband, on the one ſide, that he might not complain of ſo much Money for Rent, and on the other for Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons which you may learn in the Sequel of this Relation.</p>
            <p>We had not been Marryed for above a Fortnight, when I took occaſion to quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel with the two Maids, who ſerved my Husband during the time of his being a Widdower; for thoſe Maids not being u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to a Miſtreſs, and having infallibly heard (as I could eaſily conjecture by their Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe)
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:106022:7"/>what a Perſon I had been, they would in no wiſe ſubmit themſelves, nor ſuffer that an other ſhould have rul'd over them.</p>
            <p>In the mean while, I for my part beſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red my Jaws to ſuch purpoſe, that I kept 'em under, and if my Husband was willing to be at Reſt, he was no longer to defer turning away thoſe two Wenches. Which nevertheleſs he was very loath to do, that by what I afterwards learnt from the Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, he had lived a little more familiarly with them than Decency did allow of; but I was obliged to follow the Mode of Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men who come to Marry with Men, that is to ſay, I was to turn away the Maids, that I might have no Contradictions, for that raſcality finds ſo much to blame touching the want of experience in New Wives, that without having the greateſt patience in the World they are not to be born with.</p>
            <p>When that all things were thus ſetled, and in good Order, my Husband began diligently to attend his buſineſs at the Change, and to look after his Servants; while that for my part I took care of the Shop, wherein I became in a ſhort time as skilful and as ready, as if I had been brought up to it all my Life, which certainly is no very great Subject of Admiration; for
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:106022:8"/>there is no great Art in weighing Tobacco and filling of Pipes.</p>
            <p>In the mean while, all ſorts of Merchants and Tradeſmen came to our Houſe, tho' with no other Deſign than to ſee and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe with me, while they ſet a ſmoaking their Tobacco, which cannot be prohibited in ſuch Shops; for I was dreſs'd like a God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſs, and you would have ſaid that I was Queen of all the Tobacco-Sellers Wives. The truth is, that my Husband deſired me ſeveral times that I would lay aſide thoſe Trappings which glittered and made too great a ſhow, but all his Repreſentations were in vain, that Devil of Pride had ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken ſuch deep root in my mind, that all his endeavours to deſtroy it were in vain. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides I am not the only one who by ſuch means has butter'd and nouriſh'd her Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band's Brow-Antlets. All Women are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly proud, and tho' commonly they fall into a dirty ſluttiſhneſs when they are Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed, nevertheleſs they muſt have all manner of fine things, that they may not appear leſs than their Companions or Neighbours, without conſidering whether their Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band's Incomes can counterpoiſe that of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. They muſt have at home all manner of precious Moveables and Furniture, and if theſe poor Cullies will not conſent to
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:106022:8"/>buy them all they have a mind to, they will never have a good Look nor a kind Word from their Spouſes. Beſides theſe difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties there are ſeveral others which are from time to time, for if it happens to thoſe Creatures to have their Bellies full of Petti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toes they muſt prepare an Equipage for the little Children ſo rich and ſo pompous, that they may be an Object of Admiration to all People, and tho' they alledge for their Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification, that it ſhall be but one time for all, however I aſſure you that as ſoon as they find themſelves again in the ſame Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, they muſt again make a Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Preparations, for during that Interval all thoſe Laces have changed the Faſhion, and if the Wife does not follow the New Mode, ſhe can never happily be delivered of the Child ſhe goes with.</p>
            <p>After this manner did I live with my Husband, and though I did not put him to a Hundred Pounds Charge for Clouts, by reaſon I imagined I ſhould not lie in the firſt Year, I obliged him however to lay out ſo much Money for Moveables, Cloaths, Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nen, Laces, and ſeveral other ſuch like things, that he often ſcratched his Head, neither more nor leſs, than if he had had a great many Lice, which put him to that ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible itching. To make ſhort, I took ſuch a
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:106022:9"/>courſe, that in a Year or two our Affairs began to go backwards like a Crab, which my Husband perceiving, and ſeeing clearly that I ſhould be the cauſe of his Ruine, if he did not timely prevent it, kept his Purſe ſhut and gave me nothing more than what was neceſſary for the Maintenance of a Houſe; but becauſe I ſtill received the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney for Tobacco, it was impoſſible for him to hinder me from ſtealing from him, ſo much as in a little time amounted to a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable Sum, which I gave my Mother to keep for to make uſe of in caſe I fell into a Calamitous time, and ſhe alſo underſtood how to cheat her very dexterouſly. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he took notice that his Tobacco leſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and fell ſhort, and that no Money aroſe from it, whereupon he ratled me the firſt time very ſharply, but ſeeing that was to little purpoſe, he undertook to employ an other more powerful means, for one Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing when all the People were gone to Church, having called me into a Back-Room, he repreſented to me my Duty with ſuch very pertinent Reaſons, that I was ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſenſible of them for above a Week after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards.</p>
            <p>I could not eaſily diſgeſt this Affront, and tho' after his Anger was appeaſed, he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſought me ſeveral times, that I would think
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:106022:9"/>no more thereof, proteſting that he would never treat me after that manner, provided I would have comported my ſelf as I ought to do, nevertheleſs, I would not ſuffer him to touch me for above a Fortnight, and I not only plagued him in that reſpect, but I alſo took an irrevocable Reſolution of planting two Horns upon his Front, that in no wiſe ſhould yield to thoſe of <hi>Acteon,</hi> and exerciſe my Body in Labour as ſtrongly as ever did <hi>Lais,</hi> or <hi>Meſſalina</hi> the Wife of the Emperour <hi>Claudius.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I wanted not an occaſion to effect all this, for though above two years time, I had not done the Feat with any Body, nor had I given any one hopes of doing it, my Old <hi>Inamorato</hi>'s fail'd not ſtill of coming in Crowds to the Door, and even thoſe too who had had all their Lives long an Averſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for Tobacco, had tortur'd themſelves with ſmoaking ſince that they might have a familiar Converſation, and an honourable acceſs to my Houſe: True it is that they were to be careful how they employed then their time, becauſe that my Husband, who knew very well that I was none of the Chaſteſt, by little and little became very jealous, and for that reaſon did not look up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on any of thoſe with a good Eye in his Houſe, who had in any wiſe approached
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:106022:10"/>me before. This Reſolution having been thus taken, I ſhowed my ſelf oftner in the Street, than I had thitherto done, and deckt my ſelf ſo ſpruce and ſo fine, that I drew the Eyes of all upon me. Moreover I diſpatched my Mother to two or three of my old Gallants, alledging for pretext that ſhe had ſomething to tell them. Theſe went to her Chamber without delay, where ſhe ſtayed them ſo long with Impertinent Tat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings of one thing or other, until I had no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice thereof by a Wench that lived in that Houſe in Quality of a Maid. I went thither finely adorn'd to ſee again my ancient Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, but as if it had been by chance that I met with any one of them there, that I might ſet the better value upon my Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modity, I ſhowed my ſelf too Coy and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dainful to amuſe my ſelf in things of that Nature, inſomuch, that one would have thought it had never been toucht with a Finger, and becauſe Deſires augment by Denyal, I rendred them ſo hot that they would have given half their Eſtates, to have enjoyed my Favours, which they were ſo much the more paſſionate upon, as that they ſaw me engaged in Marriage; for that Curſed Folly ſeems to be naturally imprin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the Minds of Men, that they love much rather to Commit Adulteries, than to
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:106022:10"/>Divert themſelves with Whores, which proceeds undoubtedly from that they ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine, that Marryed Women grant them the Enjoyment of their Bodies out of pure In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination, though it be however moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain that there are ſeveral amongſt them who proſtitute themſelves much more than thoſe innocent Creatures who out of neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity are obliged to gain their Livelyhood in Bawdy Houſes. And you may be aſſured you ſimple Young or Old Lovers, that when a Woman Expoſes her ſelf thus by aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doning her ſelf to Strangers, ſhe either does it to get Money or to ſatisfy her Laſcivious Temper; if it be for the firſt Reaſon, why ſhould ſhe not endeavour to receive it from an other Perſon as well as you? And if it be to content her Luſt and Laſciviouſneſs, you may firmly believe, that not one Man nor ſix, are ſufficient to extinguiſh her Flame, and by Conſequence you cannot be the only Perſon that poſſeſſes her Favour. In ſhort, after we had thus agreed upon the Bargain for this New Maydenhead, which was not done, until a good quantity of Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver had firſt of all ſoftned the Humour (for it was particularly for my intereſt that I played at <hi>Hugh Gaffer-Cookes,</hi> tho' I was alſo ſomething provoked to it by the tick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of my own Nature) we retired then
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:106022:11"/>into the Back-Room) for I had taken two Chambers for my Mother as I told you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, though my Husband had knowledge but of one, and we there did our Work as Gentilely and as Pleaſantly as we uſed to do in former times.</p>
            <p>Nevertheleſs this Life could not laſt very long, tho' there had never been any dabling in our Water-Pots, without my Husband's knowing it, he who had padded the ſame way often in his Youth, yet he took no notice of it, but I eaſily obſerved by the coldneſs of his Carriage to me afterwards, and by all his Behaviour, that he had an Inckling of it; and if he did not tell his mind upon the buſineſs, it was for no other reaſon which obliged him to act in that manner, than to catch me in the Fact, if it was poſſible for him; but I knew how to manage my Affairs with ſo much Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpection, that for a long time it was im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible for him to bring his deſign about, though the Occaſion did often happen, and if he had known my Mother's Lodgings conſiſted in two Rooms, there would cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly have been a great deal of Buſtle a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us, for I have heard him ſeveral times in the Fore-Room, when he came to ſeek me, while I was taking my Heats in the ſame moment in the Back-Room, with
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:106022:11"/>one Gallant or other, and he had alſo once demanded of the Taylor who dwelt under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath, who it was that had that Chamber, but I had already provided againſt that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conveniency, and I had ſo well won upon that Fellow by two Silver Salts which I gave him, that he made him anſwer, that he kept it himſelf for his own uſe, inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much, that my poor Innocent Gulley could not diſcover where it was I took my Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure.</p>
            <p>In the mean while, this occaſioned our leading a very Pleaſant Life at our Home, for though he let nothing appear of ſuch a Conduct, yet he took occaſion to quarrel at all things, and often ſwinged me off, after ſo rude a manner, as if he had been to have beaten Stock-fiſh to have render'd it ſupple, which made me conceive ſuch an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion againſt him, that I could hardly any longer bear the ſight of him.</p>
            <p>But after that this ſorry courſe had la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted about ſeven or eight Months, my Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther who was my only Comfort and only Refuge, fell ſick and was reduced to that extremity, that ſhe dyed at the Weeks end, which my Husband was as joyful for as I was ſad, becauſe he hoped that when this Block was removed, I ſhould become much the better Wife. He immediately cauſed
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:106022:12"/>all the Moveables to be brought to our Houſe that were in the Fore-Room, tho' they were but of very ſmall Importance; for as for the other that I had pinched from him from time to time, and which my Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants had given me for the uſe of my Body, I locked them up in the other Chamber, which I kept ſtill for ſome time after the Death of my Mother, without my Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band's knowing the leaſt of the matter. He cauſed alſo the Corps of the Deceaſed to be brought into our Houſe, and for his own Honour, made a very great Funeral, for without that conſideration, he would have rather choſen to have flung it to the Dogs.</p>
            <p>In the mean while, as I dayly inquired after ſome place to exerciſe my Calling in in Repoſe and Liberty (for I durſt not ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture it in the Chamber I kept; becauſe that other Perſons very reſerved had taken Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of the Fore-Room, and whom I feared might go and inform my Patron if they perceived that Men came Crowding to me there, to which, my Husband had me often dogged by others, knowing that I had nothing more to do there) I was carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed one Evening into <hi>Drury-lane</hi> to a Wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows Houſe, by one of my Gallants, whom I met with by chance. The Widdow kept a Mayd, of eighteen or nineteen years of
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:106022:12"/>Age, to whom ſhe gave leave to get Money by the ſweat of her Body, that ſhe might appear in an honourable Poſture, and for that purpoſe ſhe imparted her Talent to ſome Gentlemen advanced in Years, and of a calm Humour, of whom every one had his particular day aſſigned him alone, that the others might not be taken notice of. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides this Mayd, there came alſo ſometimes when occaſion required it, ſome marryed Woman or other whoſe Husband and ſhe could not agree together as they ought to do, and who for that reaſon tranſported her ſelf into that place, that ſhe might live with another in Peace and Diverſion, ſo that this Old Woman kept a Bawdy-Houſe of Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens Wives; but after that I began to fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent it, the others had not much Practice there, for ſo rich and ſtately Apparel as I uſually wore, tho' it had not been accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied with a Beautiful Face, might eaſily attract the Admiration of a Troop of men, and eſpecially they all have ſomething of the Nature of <hi>Germans,</hi> who had rather have to do with an ugly naſty Quean in fine Cloaths, than a Beautiful Mayd in a Plain Dreſs.</p>
            <p>This Houſe of my Landladys pleaſed me extreamly, and I could willingly have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued longer than my Frequentation (for
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:106022:13"/>Money came rolling in a-pace) if an unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py Accident had not brought the buſineſs almoſt all to nothing. My Husband told me one Morning that he was to go ſettle ſome accounts, and for that purpoſe within a Week or eight days, he was to take a Jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney to <hi>Northampton</hi> and ſome other places thereabouts, as indeed, after having made great Preparations for his Journey, he took his leave of me at the time he ſpoke of, with Teſtimonies of Affection, much greater than ordinary. You may very well think, that I was not very ſad at his Departure, for I promiſed my ſelf that during that time, I ſhould have Elbow-room, and might heap up a Sum of Money; which I had ſo much the more reaſon to do, as that I was to make my eſcape, when I had provided my ſelf with the Profits that I had honourably gained by the Labour of my Body, as alſo all that I could ſcrape up in the management of our Trade and Houſe-Keeping, that then I would withdraw for a long time, and Exchange <hi>London</hi> for ſome other Town, which proceeded from the Averſion I had conceived to my Husband, ſince the firſt time he had chaſtiſed me ſo ſeverely. This Aver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion was encreaſed to that degree, that I had all the Pains imaginable to bear the ſight of him, wherein I reſembled moſt
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:106022:13"/>Women who are commonly blind in all their Paſſions, and are ſo violently paſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate in their hatred or their Love, even moſt commonly without any Cauſe, that they exceed all Bounds.</p>
            <p>Three or four days after that my Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band was gone, I went to my Widdow's Houſe, and gave her to underſtand, that I ſhould have henceforward the occaſion to be employed in the Service of an honeſt Man without running any Riſque; and certainly I was not long without putting in Practice ſo laudable an Exerciſe, and there preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly after a Man came in who approached me, and who having an ugly Wife, diverted himſelf ſometimes with thoſe of other Mens, though perhaps he would have done no leſs, if he had had a fair one; for even the moſt dainty Meats cauſe at length Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt, if you eat them continually. It ſeems as if Nature for the Mortification of Honeſt Women, has ſo deeply imprinted this abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable deſire in the Hearts of Men, that they cannot get rid of it. And methinks they would be in this Caſe in leſs manner excuſable, if they ſought after Women, tho' none of the greateſt Beauties, yet who ought not to yield that advantage to the others, that belong to them; but O! the Prodigiouſneſs of diſorderly Love: We ſee
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:106022:14"/>Husbands who have Wives as beautiful as Angels, who nevertheleſs run after Wenches, who are more deformed and ugly than if they were Devils; but if thoſe Women did as I was uſed to do, I am ſure that thoſe Gallants would find them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves much more aſſiduous at their own Homes, for fear that during their abſence, their Wives ſhould diſhonour them in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king them bear the Arms and Crown of the Cornutors: And why ſhould our Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom be leſs than that of the Men, in what concerns the violation of the Conjugal Oath? Perhaps I ſhall be anſwered as to that point, that this is the cauſe that Families are baſtardized; but where can one find a Medium in this Affair, and if all thoſe who fall into ſuch extravagancies, govern them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves after the ſame manner that I did, let 'em take my word it would be a great Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digy if ever they come to Baſtardize a Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for the <hi>Field produces abundance of Herbs, but the High-way has not this advantage;</hi> from whence comes then this diſorder, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs it be that Men have eſtabliſhed Laws; and when once the Women ſhall have in their hands the Helm of the Government, things will have another Byaſs? But not to Moralize too long upon this Point, and not to ſuffer my ſelf to be tranſported in
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:106022:14"/>this manner by the fervency of my Zeal, I may once more return into the way I ought to keep, and paſs over ſuch things as are the leaſt neceſſary to my Subject; for will it not be better in imitation of the Shoe-ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, I hold exactly to the form of the Laſt, ſince beſides, my Wit is not ſtrong e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to make ſuch like Sallys, and that tho' they ſhould be done pat and to the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, I ſhall only loſe my time in employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing my Leiſure therein?</p>
            <p>Wherefore to return to my Subject, I will tell the <hi>Reader,</hi> that three days after that my Husband was departed, that fore-men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned Widdow came to my Houſe, and beſought me, ſince too I had no Body to be afraid of, that I would come and ſpend one Night in her Houſe, proteſting to me, that I ſhould have to do with a Man, that ſhe would be Surety that I ſhould be well paid by. I ask't her what ſort of Man it was, and if I had never had his Company before. Thereupon ſhe anſwered me in the Negative, and that he was of an Humour not to be known by any Body. I remained a long time wavering if I ſhould conclude or no this Bargain: For to paſs a whole Night out of my Houſe, methought too difficult a matter to effect, without my Servants having ſome knowledge thereof or
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:106022:15"/>ſome ill ſuſpicion; and as for worldly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits I would not have hazarded my ſelf ſo far; for theſe Creatures are often filled with Malice, and when they have once diſcover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that you have committed any ſuch fault, you are always afterwards under their Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection, without it's being poſſible for you to ſhake off this Yoke in any manner, and there is danger that their blabbing and long Tongues may make you loſe your honour, or at leaſt your good reputation. Now as for your honour it is to be ſuppoſed abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely loſt, when thoſe Queans of Maids have once began to obſerve your Actions and Criticiſe your Conduct.</p>
            <p>Nevertheleſs, as the Power of Money has ever had an abſolute Dominion over my Mind, and as I was in hopes to behave my ſelf ſo well in my Affairs, that no Body ſhould know any thing thereof, I promiſed to come to her accordingly, upon Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that it ſhould be after eleven of the Clock, and that I ſhould ſtay no longer than five of the Clock in the Morning; for it was in <hi>Autumn,</hi> which is a Seaſon dark enough to come back to one's Houſe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out being taken notice of by the Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours. I proteſt to you, Deareſt Madam (ſaid the Widdow, as ſoon as I had given her my Word) that I ſhall be obliged to
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:106022:15"/>you all the reſt of my Life: For that Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman told me this morning, that he has been ſo tranſported with Love for you theſe two or three days laſt paſt that he has ſeen you, that he promiſed me three Guin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neys, in caſe that by my means he could bring about his Deſign: From whence you may conjecture, added ſhe, how great the Recompence will be that you are to expect. Theſe Reaſons were the Cauſe that I made my ſelf very fine, and I intended to make him pay dear enough for my Commodity. But Affairs have not always that Succeſs that People do imagine to themſelves; and we often find our ſelves very villainouſly miſtaken when that we have not any Suſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picion of Deceit and Treachery.</p>
            <p>As ſoon as it was Ten a Clock our Shop was ſhut up, as was cuſtomary, and our Maids were gone to Bed before Eleven, at which time I was to be at the Rendezvouz appointed; ſo that I had no reaſon to fear, becauſe they lay in a Room ſo far towards the Backſide of our Houſe, that tho' they had been awake, it would have been im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible they ſhould have heard me open and ſhut the Door, tho' I had done it leſs gently. Whereupon I ſet out, after hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing decked my ſelfe to ſome purpoſe; and having taken a Coach at ſome diſtance from
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:106022:16"/>our Houſe, I came to the Widows about half an hour after Eleven: I ask'd her im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately if the Gentleman was yet come? She made me Anſwer, that he had waited for me above an hour and an half; but that he would not that any one ſhould ſee him, and that he had given her in Charge, that ſhe ſhould only put me to Bed, and that he would come to me in the dark. I was not over-well pleaſed with this new Freak of his; and from the Beginning I ſeemed to have ſome Repugnance thereto: But foraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as that I did not much care ſo I got but Money, whether it was with handſom or ugly Men: And beſides, as I knew, that there are ſeveral who have this Maggot in their Heads of not being willing to be ſeen, imagining they ſhall not be known again, I was prevailed with at length, and was put to Bed in a Chamber where I had done that Feat ſeveral other times, according as Occaſions were offered; and there I wait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for my Spark whom I intended to fleece to ſome purpoſe.</p>
            <p>Preſently after, the ſame Widow con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducted this Cavalier to my Bed ſide, by fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of the Darkneſs; and he having im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately embraced and kiſſed me ſeveral times, put off his, Cloaths and lay ſoft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly down by my Side, without uttering
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:106022:16"/>one word, but by way of Whiſpers, and through his Teeth, inſomuch that I could never judge by that kind of murmur of his voice if I had had any Acquaintance with him before. Thus after we had paſs'd our time in wantoning and toying, till half an hour after Twelve, he pretended that he would go Sleep; but I could eaſily hear that he caſt out ſome Sighs by Intervals, which proceeded from the Bottom of his Heart. I was ſo much amazed at this, that I took the Reſolution of going to ſeek for Light, as ſoon as I could perceive he was faſt aſleep, to ſee if I knew this languiſhing Lover. A little after I thought that Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven or Hell (it was certainly one of the two) would favour my Undertaking; whereof there was no other cauſe, as I ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine, than his Wearineſs which proceeded from his voluptuous Combat: For we had been very brisk, and heated our ſelves to ſome purpoſe in our amorous Conflict. Whereupon I got up ſoftly from him, and having put on my Petticoat, I went be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, where I found the Woman of the Houſe faſt aſleep, with the Maid, who was one of <hi>Venus</hi>'s Nuns. Having taken the Lamp which hung ſtill lighted in the Chim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, I went up above again bare footed, with out making any Noiſe: For I thought
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:106022:17"/>it not convenient to awake them: But who can expreſs the Fright and Conſternation I was in, when I found that he with whom I had had ſo great an Aſſault was my own Husband, who without doubt came thither to convict me of my whoring, after having for a long while had Suſpition thereof. I ſwear to you, that I was ſo terrified, that the Lamp had like to have fallen out of my Hand. Nevertheleſs, as I have always been endowed with a wonderful preſence of Wit, I ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what recollected my Sences, and conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the greatneſs of the Danger I ſhould be in if he ſaw me there, I took all my Cloaths under my Arms, and went imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately down Stairs, and flung my ſelf ſtraight into the Widows Bed, who I had all the reaſon imaginable to ſuſpect had played me this Pranck. The Truth is, that I told her, as ſoon as I had awaked her, that I could not have believed that ſhe would have committed ſo curſed an Infide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity towards me as to— How, ſaid the poor Woman, interrupting my Diſcourſe, have I done any thing to you that is contrary to the Duty of Civility, Honeſty and Friendſhip. As we had not time to uſe many words, I ask'd her im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately who had brought that Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man to her Houſe? And having conjectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:106022:17"/>by her Anſwer, that ſhe was innocent in this Encounter, as this might eaſily be true: For before that time ſhe had never ſeen my Husband, nor ſet Foot in our Houſe, but only when ſhe brought me this Meſſage. I related to her how all went, beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging her Advice at the ſame time, what was the beſt Courſe for me to take in this Occaſion. The poor Woman was ſo trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled and concerned that ſhe could hardly utter one word. I lay apart the Counſel ſhe would have given me. In the mean while, there came a thing into my Fancy, which I thought the moſt ſuitable in the world to free me out of that Diſquiet. I gave this woman the three Guinneys my Husband had promiſed her, and engaged to give her as many more in caſe ſhe would be faithful to me, and declare ſhe had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver any Acquaintance with me; then I gave the Damoſel who dwelt in the Houſe a Guinney, upon condition ſhe would go lie in my place; and that when my <hi>Husband</hi> ſhould come to wake, ſhe ſhould by one means or other give him to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, that during all the Night long he had lain with no other Perſon than her ſelf. This Damoſel, who perhaps had not got ſo much money in a Fortnight, was eaſily prevailed upon by ſuch Pathetick Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:106022:18"/>and the Landlady led her to the Bed in the Dark. This was done with ſo much Cunning that my Husband had not the leaſt Inckling thereof. When I had diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed all things in due manner, I went out of the Houſe about Three of the Clock in the Night, told the Watch I met with, that I had been at a Womans Labour, without making known to the Widow, that I had a Deſign to return thither once again, as I thought I was obliged to do for the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſecuring my Honour. I only told her, that ſhe ſhould diſſemble her ever having ſeen me, not only to my Husband, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo to all others who had been in my Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany.</p>
            <p>But when I had paſs'd through two Streets by the Watch in this manner in the Dark, I ask'd one of the Watch if he would guard me home to my Houſe; which I did for a reaſon I am going to inform my Reader of immediately. This Fellow took immediately his Lanthorn, and without making any further Enquiry while we were going along, and were both talking of ſeveral Adventures, I ask'd him if he would do me a piece of Service, aſſuring him, that I would honeſtly reward him. I added, that he would have nothing more to do, than to come about Five a Clock to the Houſe I
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:106022:18"/>would ſhow him, and tell the perſon who ſhould open him the Door, that he muſt of neceſſity ſpeak to me in private. He promiſed me he would not fail upon Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition I would pay him well for his Pains.</p>
            <p>Then I opened the Door as gently as was poſſible for me to do; where after having in great haſte put all things into good Order, I went to Bed with neither more nor leſs Concern than if I had lain there all the Night long. No ſooner had it ſtruck Five, than that the aforeſaid Watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man came knocking to ſome purpoſe at our Door, without the poor man's knowing of any other Meſſage he had to do there; for I made no other Declaration to him of the Buſineſs; but that he was to ſpeak to me in private, and that he was to do it without any Body's being by. I had a Bell hanging by my Bed ſide, which I rang ſo long, until that one of the Maids got up, and asked me what I wanted? I told her, that I heard a ſtrange knocking at the Door, and that ſhe was to go, and ſee who it was that made ſuch a Noiſe. <hi>Betty,</hi> ſo was the Maid called, came back preently to my Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and told me, that there was one of the Watch at the Door, who ſaid, that he had ſomething of Moment to acquaint me
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:106022:19"/>with; but that as it was ſtill very dark ſhe durſt not open the Door. What a Fool you are, ſaid I to her, what hurt is there to fear from Perſons who are ſet on purpoſe to hinder others from committing any miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief. Open the Door, added I, you fright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Fool you, and let us hear what this man has to ſay. Whereupon the Watchman was let into the Houſe, and then into my Room, where, according to the Order he had, he would not utter a word until I had put the Maid out. When I thought he had been there long enough to have told a Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage of ſome Buſineſs of Importance, I gave him ſome Money to drink; and all un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſt as I was in my Night-Gown, I led him out of the Door. Ah Heavens! cried I, as ſoon as ever he was gone, wringing my hands, and letting abundance of Tears trickle down my Cheeks, Is it poſſible, is it poſſible, ſaid I again, that ſuch Actions ſhould remain unpuniſhed! It is a Prodigy, added I, that the Earth does not open to ſwallow up all alive thoſe who commit ſuch Abominations: And thereupon pour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forth again a Torrent of Tears, I made my Looks ſeem ſuch that it might have been painted for the Face of Sadneſs it ſelf. In the mean while <hi>Betty</hi> conſidered me as a diſtracted Perſon, not knowing what to
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:106022:19"/>think of ſo ſuddain an Affliction. The Noiſe I made obliged the other Maid to come running to me, and ſeeing her Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs in ſo lamentable a pickle ſhe began at firſt to ask what the matter was; what it was that rendred me ſo ſad and ſo void of Comfort: But I let her ask the ſame thing ten times over, before I made her any Anſwer: Howling in the mean while after ſuch a Rate, as if I had been in the greateſt Affliction imaginable. My dear Girles, ſaid I to them at length, do not wonder to ſee me grieve at this rate: I have word juſt now brought me, that my <hi>Husband,</hi> whom we thought gone to <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thampton,</hi> is in Bed with a Strumpet; and in the mean while he daily blames and ſcolds at me, that we gain nothing by our Trade. Ah! Madam, ſaid <hi>Betty,</hi> you muſt not lay all things thus to heart: Perhaps that ſome of your Enemies have ſet on foot this Rumor only to grieve and vex you: I would not believe it, continued ſhe, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs I had ſeen it with mine own Eyes: There is probability enough of it's being ſo, replied I, for I am told the very place, inſomuch that we cannot be miſtaken: Let us but go thither immediately; for it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible for me to live any longer in the Uncertainty of this Buſineſs: Thereupon I
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:106022:20"/>bid <hi>Betty</hi> dreſs her, as I did my ſelf, and thus at Break of Day we went together to <hi>Drury Lane.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As ſoon as the Landlady had opened the Door, I gave her a wink, which ſerved for a Signal, that ſhe ſhould not contradict her ſelf; and at the ſame time turning to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards my Maid, I ask'd her if we had hit the right place, and if there was any need of enquiring any farther? The Landlady looked fixedly upon me, juſt like a Ninny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hammer, not knowing what to think of my Proceedings. In the mean time up Stairs we went, where my brave Spark was aſleep with a Damoſel lying by his Side. What do you think, <hi>Betty,</hi> ſaid I to my Maid, and am I now in the wrong? And could you ever have believed that this Rogue ſhould ſo violate the Oath of Fidelity; and doſt thou not ſee that by his diſorderly Life I ſhall at length be reduced to Pover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Begging? Ah, purſued I, how wretched are women when they have ſuch <hi>Husbands!</hi> Ah, how great is their Folly, and their Error, when they believe the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtations of theſe deceitful men, who exalt above the Clouds that pretended Affection wherewith they flatter the poor Sex! Theſe words were ſtill accompanied with many other Lamentations, and made ſuch a noiſe
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:106022:20"/>that they awaked my <hi>Husband;</hi> who with his Eyes half open, and ſeeing me as one dreſt, and by his Bed Side with my Maid; and ſeeing alſo another Woman lying by him, was in ſuch a Maze, that he could hard<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly utter a word. He look'd upon her inceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſantly, and lifted up his Eyes towards Heaven, as it were to have Compaſſion of his miſerable Condition. Well Spark, well Gallant, ſaid I to him, ſeizing him by the Sleeve, there needed not much time to fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh your Journey, ſince the places are no farther diſtant than our Houſe. But, added I, we ſhall take care henceforward, with the good Pleaſure of God, I ſhall prevent this Damoſels poſſeſſing my place, though, purſued I, the beſt courſe would be that I troubled my ſelf no farther, but abſent my ſelf from you. By that means I ſhall avoid the Danger there is of being infected with ſome filthy contagious Diſeaſe, which ſuch a Life as you lead muſt infallibly plunge you into ſooner or later. In the mean while my Husband leap'd out of Bed, and called the Maid aſide, whom he ask'd where I had lain that Night, while I pretended to ſcold with the Wench and Landlady, who were no leſs frighted than if the Sky had fallen upon their heads.</p>
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:106022:21"/>
            <p>That poor ſilly Maid, who was not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver well acquainted with my Tricks, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſted to him upon her Conſcience, that I had been all the Night long in Bed at our Houſe, and began to relate to him after what manner we had had Notice of this Affair. He was a long while without uttering ſo much as a word, holding his Eyes fixed upon the Floor; but at length he lifted them up to look upon me after a terrible manner. I am, ſaid he then, I am deceived on the one ſide or other; however, I do really fancy, that I heard your Voice more than once this Night; but, added he at length, I ought to have conſidered on your Bitchery before I married you; But you may well fear the Effects of my juſt Anger, if ever I catch you in a Fault; and for your parts, ſaid he, turning towards the landlady and the Whore, who had lain with him, you ſhall know in a ſhort time, that I have practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the world too well not to be jilted and laugh'd at with Impunity. Thereupon he put on his Sword, and went out of the Bawdy-houſe, without giving Ear to a word more, which I was not very ſorry for, becauſe I was ſtill in the greateſt Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiet imaginable, fearing the Widow or Whore would come to contradict them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; and for my part, that I might no
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:106022:21"/>longer be expoſed, I thought convenient to follow my Husband's Example, inſomuch that I left thoſe two women in ſo great an Amazement, that I do not believe, that they ever were in ſuch a Condition.</p>
            <p>Being returned home, I found my Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band in the Shop, leaning upon one of his Arms, and full of ſo many Thoughts, that he took Notice neither of me nor the Maid; but a Volley of injurious Language and Curſes which I flung in his Teeth, quickly awaked him out of his Dumps; yet as he had reaſon enough to take another Courſe (for as I have already told you, he had heard me rail againſt him more than once) he held his Peace, and went behind the Counter: But his Looks made me ſufficiently obſerve, that he had not an over firm Belief, that I had paſſed that Night in our Houſe. I after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards took incredible Pains to learn who it was that had carried my Husband into that Place; But I could not diſcover it till a long time after, when that by chance I found a Letter that cleared the Buſineſs, and which the Reader ſhall be acquainted with in the Sequel of this Hiſtory. After this Adventure we were about three weeks with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſetting our Horſes together: But to confeſs the Truth, it was not that I was afraid of any Venereal Infection, My only
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:106022:22"/>Diſquiet, was, that one Night or other he would play me ſome Prank, which I ſhould keep the Remembrance of all the reſt of my Life. However we terminated at length our Quarrel, and the two Parties were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain reconciled to one another: But the firſt Night of our Re-union was not ſo well ſolemnized as my <hi>Husband</hi> had done when we lay together at another Lodging in <hi>Drury Lane,</hi> tho' I infallibly believe there was no other Cauſe that obliged him to make then ſo great an Effort, than to hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der me from having any Suſpicion, and to reward me afterwards to ſome Purpoſe for thoſe willing and vigorous Repartees.</p>
            <p>Perhaps that ſome innocent Creature will imagine, that the Conſtitution of his Thing, and his way of Performing ſhould have made me ſenſible with whom I had to do: moſt of thoſe filly Maidens may be pleaſed to know, that there are ſo many of thoſe Inſtrumets which reſemble one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in Length and Bigneſs, that there is no great Reliance to be had thereupon; and that you may not be obliged to believe me alone, enquire of all thoſe brave Women, who abandon themſelves ſometimes to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers than their <hi>Husbands,</hi> they will un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly affirm the ſame thing, unleſs they are deſirous to diſown what they are
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:106022:22"/>and what they do. Since that dear Night with which far from gaining me a conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Sum of Money, as I had been made to hope for, had made me disburſe ſufficient to have purchaſed thoſe two above mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Women, I durſt not ſet my Foot again into that houſe; and I had very ſeldom the opportunity to go into other Places, by reaſon my <hi>Husband</hi> ſeldom let me go out without having ſome body to keep me Company. This way of Living, was ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry tedious and troubleſome to my humor; and yet I was conſtrained to ſubmit to it if I intended to make my <hi>Husband</hi> believe that I played him no foul play. In the mean while my Lovers were continually poaching about our houſe, which was the greateſt Puniſhment to me in the World: For be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides my knowing how to make my Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kets with them, there were ſome of 'em whoſe Embraces pleas'd me much more than thoſe of my own <hi>Husband,</hi> who dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly became more and more inſupportable to me: Yet at length I had an Opportunity to have an amorous Ticket delivered to two of them, frm whom in a little time I had gained by my Service a paſſable Sum of money. Whereupon I wrote to him, that the day following between eleven and twelve, I would meet him at a certain Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:106022:23"/>in <hi>Covent Garden,</hi> which had the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation of a Civil Houſe, and was ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed to Ladies, and a great Nurſery of Gallantry.</p>
            <p>I had ſeveral times been in this Tavern with that Gentleman, to whom I was well aſſured they would not refuſe him any Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniencies, by reaſon they could not in any wiſe tax him of being ſtingy and avaricious. Beſides, the appointment of this Rendez<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouz, I ſet down to him the manner after which he was to comport himſelf in this Juncture of Affairs, adding to him, that I expected no Anſwer from him, that ſo we might not be hinder'd in the Proſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Deſign I had.</p>
            <p>The day after I pretended going to the Market, and my Husband having ſent one of the Maids with me, according to his Cuſtom; we walked very modeſtly along, till we came juſt before the Tavern, where I was ſure my honeſt Spark had taken all the neceſſary Orders; as we alſo found in the twinckling of an Eye: For a Drawer and one of the Maids were before the Door, where they made a Shew of tickling one another; but another Drawer in the Balco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, pretending as if he did it to ſpoil their Sport, powred upon us a Chamber-Pot full of Water, inſomuch that it ran from our
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:106022:23"/>Heads to our Toes. I turned my ſelf imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately, and tho' I had given order for this in my Letter, yet I made ſo horrible a Clamour, that in a Moment there were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove Fifty perſons before the Door.</p>
            <p>In the mean while the Landlady came out to me, and deſired me with the moſt Civil words imaginable, that I would do her the Honour to go into her Houſe, ſaying, that ſhe was extreamly ſorry that the Draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, by a piece of inſolence, which neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs he ſhould pay dear for, had brought that Miſchance upon my Head. At firſt I ſeem'd wholly averſe to make uſe of her offer; but at length my Cloaths were ſo wet, that I made a Shew of finding my ſelf forced to accept of it. I went into the Houſe, and ſo into a little Room, where Faggots were immediately lighted. Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently after I ſent my Maid home, tho' ſhe was little drier than my ſelf, that ſhe might go fetch me other Aparrel; which ſhe could not do, nor put on freſh Cloaths her ſelf in leſs than an hours time. The poor Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture trembled with Cold, and would wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly have ſtaid by the Fire a little longer; but I thought not convenient to defer any longer ſuch precious moments.</p>
            <p>As ſoon as this Creature was gone, I was lead into another Chamber, where my Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:106022:24"/>who had almoſt ſplit his Sides with laughing (conſidering the good Succeſs of this Enterpriſe) waited for me with ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tream Patience, and without amuzing our ſelves, and loſing of time, in making a great number of impertinent Complements, and ridiculous Chatterings: For not only Hours, but Minutes were precious to us at that time: We got upon our Bed, and did our Buſineſs at ſo ſwinging a Rate, that that day I was no leſs ſprinkled within than without—</p>
            <p>After we had ſpent above half an hour in taking our Pleaſures, I took my leave for to withdraw into my little Room; where having found the Woman of the houſe, who had all the while ſtood Senti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel, I ſate down with her by the Fire, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til that my Maid brought me other Cloaths.</p>
            <p>Tho' my Husband in his Youth had much frequented the voluptuous Sinks, yet he knew not at this time, that this Affair had been contrived in this manner, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that he had never known this Tavern otherwiſe than a houſe where the People would not have in any manner ſuffered ſuch things to be committed: And he was not the only Perſon herein deceived, but all thoſe too who ever haunted that Houſe.
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:106022:24"/>For all was done then with ſo much Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quility, that the leaſt thing could never have been perceived; and before they let you know of that Conveniency, they muſt have found you perſons liberal, and ſuch as might be truſted and confided in: But at preſent the Vintners of the principal Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verns are not ſo ſcrupulous; and tho' they know with what Deſign a Man and Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man comes to their Houſe, yet they will not refuſe them a Room: So that we may with Juſtice ſay that moſt of the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verns in <hi>London</hi> are at preſent Bawdy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſes; and that there is no difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them and Bawdy honſes, than that there they ask you no Money for the uſe of the Bed.</p>
            <p>A little after this Adventure, as I was going one morning up into our Garret, I found a Letter upon the Stairs, juſt by my Husband's Study, which without doubt he had by chance let fall out of his Pocket. Curioſity made me open it without think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing however that I ſhould find therein ſomething of Importance; but I was much ſurprized, and ſtrangely amazed when I ſaw that it contained what follows in very good and expreſſive Characters.</p>
            <pb n="46" facs="tcp:106022:25"/>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Sir,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>I Was very much grieved when I ſaw you married to that Woman who is at preſent your Wife; but I was much more concerned, when I heard ſhe Jilted you all manner of Ways. If you are willing to be perfectly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed as to this Affair, get by one means or other to a certain Widows Houſe, called Mrs. <hi>G</hi>— in <hi>Drury-Lane,</hi> and be aſſured, that by the help of Money you will come to the Knowledge of more than you deſire. I do not tell you how you are to comport your ſelf in ſuch Encounters, ſince you have had ſufficient Experience of 'em, not to want Cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in thoſe Occaſions. Neither did I think it convenient to diſcourſe you by word of mouth, fearing it might put you out of Countenance. Believe only, that as I am your Friend, ſo I love to keep things ſecret: Provide againſt this Diſorder the ſooneſt you can poſſibly.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>I remained very much troubled when I had read this Letter, and then was out of the Doubt and Suſpence I had ſo long been in: For I had applyed my Thoughts to a thouſand things for the endeavouring to diſcover what it was that could have brought my Husband to the forementioned place: But at the ſame time I took alſo the
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:106022:25"/>Reſolution of being ſo reveng'd at one time or other, that this Tale-bearer ſhould remember it for a long time: For it was not neceſſary to ſee the Name, ſince I had received ſeveral from the ſame hand, as well before, as ſince the day of my Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, tho' there had been a falling out be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween us for ſome time, becauſe he would have enjoyed my Body without being at a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Charges, which is a thing I could very rarely be brought to; and undoubtedly Spite and Vexation had inſpired him with this Genteel Pranck.</p>
            <p>As ſoon as I was got down again I flung this Letter into the Fire, not being willing to put it up; and beſides, I was afraid if I had kept it, it might have been found a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout me, which would have been taken for a Sign that I was not at all concern'd at it. In the mean while I loſt no occaſion of playing my part ſometimes, tho' all the manner of Stratagems which I put in Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice had not over often a happy Succeſs: Wherefore I wrote a Letter to that Spark who had ſo ſwingingly beſprinkled me, and for whom I had without Diſſimula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion a great deal more Affection than for my own Husband; and I gave him to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, that he ſhould make uſe of all
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:106022:26"/>manner of means to inſinuate himſelf into the Eſteem and Friendſhip of my Husband; For I was in hopes that by ſo doing, he would furniſh me at leaſt with the Satisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of ſeeing him oftner than I had then the Opportunity: To which I was incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with ſo much the more Paſſion, in that I promiſed my ſelf to find his Viſits infallibly followed by ſome Preſents, which he would be obliged to make me for to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe the more of my Heart and Affection: For it is a certain thing, that Money is the moſt Powerful means to make a Conqueſt over a Womans Heart. This Friendſhip was no very difficult matter to contract, ſeeing I had acquired this Lover at the time of our Wedding; and by conſequence my <hi>Husband</hi> could not be prepoſſeſſed with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ill Opinion of him. And indeed I quickly ſaw him ſeated at our Table, and afterwards he frequented our houſe with ſo much Familiarity as one of the neareſt Relations, to which the Wife he had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributed very much, becauſe that ſhe was not ugly; and that he for his, part knew how to comport himſelf with ſo moderate a Reſervedneſs, as if he had been of the Number of thoſe who keep the Great <hi>Turk</hi>'s Concubines. This Friendſhip aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:106022:26"/>to ſuch a Pitch, that he frequently brought his Wife to our Houſe, that he might make my Husband ſo much the leſs ſuſpect that he came with any Deſign upon me.</p>
            <p>This Acquaintance of ours had laſted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout four Months, and during all that ſpace of time he had hardly had ſo many Oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunites to teſtifie to me his Love as there had been Months paſſed. One certain Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternoon, as we were ſitting talking in the Parlour after Dinner, ſome Merchants ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a mind to ſee ſome Rolls of Tobacco, ſent for my Husband out. Immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly my Lover flew and took me about the Neck, and kiſſed me with ſo much Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vency and Eagerneſs, that his whole Body was ſeized with a Shivering; and not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting that my Patron would return ſo ſoon, we began a Game which had like to have coſt us our Lives: For we had hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly half done the Feat, when my Husband, who was not entirely cured of his Jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, came in ſoftly behind us, and found us in the Poſture of one upon the other. Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Whore, ſaid he, as ſoon as he was got into the Room, I have now at length caught thee at what I ſo long watched for; But, added he, you two ſhall not go glory with your having made this Bargain; and then,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:106022:27"/>thruſting his hand into his Pocket, he would infallibly have effected his Word, if my Servant had not taken me off his Knee, and leap'd upon him. Certainly when I think ſtill of that Combat, tho' at that time I was under the ſaddeſt Affliction imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, I cannot forbear laughing; for that my Lover not having time ſufficient to put himſelf in Order, his Shirt hung out of his Breeches, and what with that, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thing of greater Conſequence that was to be ſeen, it was the pleaſanteſt Sight that ever my Eyes ſaw.</p>
            <p>The two combating Parties fell at length ſo violently to work, and ſtruggled ſo hard, that at laſt they fell over one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, which gave me room enough to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcape out of the Parlour, wherein I had till then expected every moment to have had my Throat Cut. I ran in all haſte to the Room where we lay, where I took in all haſte a little Trunck, in which was my Jewels: For not being willing to forget them in ſuch a Neceſſity, I ſeized on them with all ſpeed, and decamped from the Houſe, and withdrew to the Room which I had always kept, and ſent for the Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgion, that he might let me Blood: For I had been in that Emotion, that I did not
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:106022:27"/>doubt but to fall into ſome great Fit of Sickneſs by reaſon thereof: But no ſooner were ſome ounces of Blood taken from me, than that I found my ſelf very much at eaſe, and within a day or two after I was as brisk as I had been before.</p>
            <p>There were ſeveral reaſons which made me think it convenient after three or four days to abandon that Room, and to take a Houſe where I might be ſomething far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther diſtant from the Eyes of my Husband: For when I thought but of him I trembled for Fear: Whereupon I took a Houſe in <hi>York Buildings,</hi> which tho' it were near the Court, and therefore as the World goes, now one ſhould think not over-charged with; yet as Perſons of Quality and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate flock about that end of the Town; yet as I had the Art of Jilting to Perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, I was in hopes my Gains would be pretty conſiderable in thoſe Quarters.</p>
            <p>But the Truth is, when I make Refle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction upon the Diſquiet which attends thoſe who lead a diſorderly Life, I cannot ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently admire that there are Perſons who commit ſuch Sins, without being obliged thereto by Neceſſity: For to ſee a Woman abandon her ſelf to Pleaſure, for the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining her ſelf in a handſome Eſtate and
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:106022:28"/>Condition; and who has not nevertheleſs the Conveniencies, is methinks in ſome manner worthy of being excuſed, becauſe that Poverty is a very terrible thing; and beſides it is very troubleſome, nay, almoſt inſupportable for Perſons who have been well bred and born, when they are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain'd to ſubject themſelves to go to Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice; but as for thoſe Women who give themſelves to thoſe villanous Abominations, when Miſery does not force them ſo to do, Methinks there is nothing in the World that merits more Blame and Chaſtiſement; and tho' I have liv'd my ſelf after the ſame manner that I now give the Relation of, yet I can declare to you, that I would not counſel others to follow my Example, if they are willing to have their Minds at Peace and Quiet: For when you are once engaged in Marriage, if you violate the Faith you have promiſed, I aſſure you that you loſe all the Pleaſure, thro' Diſquiet, in doing a thing which ought to be done without any Fear. Quite on the contrary we all find real Pleaſures in the practiſe of Vertue, it maintains the Mind in an agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Tranquility: It fills the Soul with an Interiour Joy. It— But hold! I ſhall preſently fall into a Province that I am not
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:106022:28"/>very well acquainted with: For not to lye, it is not long ſince I have made Profeſſion of being vertuous; and perhaps I ſhould not yet ſay a word of the Care and trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, if I had ſtill that Beauty which I was endued with formerly: But I think it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient to pawſe a while upon this Point, not to give the Reader an Occaſion to have too good, or too ill an Opinion of my Life.</p>
            <p>But as ſoon as I was got into Poſſeſſion of my new Quarters, I bethought my ſelf of going to learn what had been the Iſſue of the Battel between my Lover and my Husband: Whereupon I went one Morning betimes to a Tavern near my Lover's Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitation, and ſent him a Letter by the Draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, that if he could not come convenient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to me there, he ſhould nevertheleſs not fail of coming to my Lodging that ſame day, telling him in the Letter where it was.</p>
            <p>The Drawer acquitted himſelf dexte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly of his Meſſage; but ſome Affairs hindering my Spark at that time, he ſent me word, that my Commands ſhould be performed in the other place. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon I returned home, not in the leaſt doubting but that my Enterprize would
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:106022:29"/>be attended with the effect I expected.</p>
            <p>Towards the Evening this honeſt Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman came to my Lodging, and after ſome amorous Embraces, I asked him how he had diſingaged himſelf from the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned Diſorder? He made me Anſwer, that he had got the Victory over his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagoniſt. But, purſued he, when your Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band knew that you had made your E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcape, and that he had not Strength e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to overcome me, he cried out ſo long for help, that at length I heard ſome of his Workmen coming down Stairs, which put me into ſuch a Fright, that away got I out of the Houſe, without ſo much as thinking of taking my Cloak along with me: For the Servants were already almoſt at the Bottom: the Maid who was in the Shop, thinking ſhe could ſtop me; but ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king her by the Arm, and flinging her in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a Corner, I got into the Street, and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king a Coach, I went to the <hi>Half Moon</hi> Tavern in the <hi>Strand,</hi> whither I ſent for ſome of my Friends, and ſo paſt away my time till it was late, when coming home to my Houſe, I found that your Husband had been already there; ſo that my Wife made me the fineſt Speech that was ever read in any Hiſtory. I would willingly have diſown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:106022:29"/>the Matter; but having been forced to leave my Cloak in the Hurry, and that your Husband had brought it to our houſe with weeping Eyes, my Wife would not have given the leaſt Credit to my Diſcourſe; but this Storme is almoſt already wholly appeas'd: Nevertheleſs, have a Care on both Sides, continued he, for my Wife has vowed your Ruine, as well as your Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band.</p>
            <p>But as I was ſo far out of their Reach, theſe Menaces produced ſo little Effect in my heart, that I was not in the leaſt pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler or redder; and far from having any Fear, I deſired my Gallant to continue to me his Viſits with all manner of Boldneſs, for which we had, methoughts both of us ſufficient Reaſons, ſince we had both been in the ſame Peril; and indeed he was not neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligentin the Execution of this order: For he came to ſee me almoſt every day, and paid me ſo liberally for the Favours he had obtained from me, that during all the time he frequented me, I had not any reaſon to complain of his Generoſity.</p>
            <p>As I had already dwelt ſome time in that place, I began to think on him who had ſent that curſed Letter to my Husband. I was conſidering how I could reward him
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:106022:30"/>for his Pains, and I fancied I had at length found the Opportunity, he being married, as were moſt of my Lovers: I was not long contriving the means to effect this, before that I had managed my Deſign with ſo much Cunning, that he came at length to my Houſe: For tho' he had play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed me that Prank, it was not for want of Love; but only by reaſon I would not comply with his covetous Humor.</p>
            <p>I quickly began to make him believe by all the means imaginable, that I was ſo far tranſported with Love for him, that I could hardly live in his Abſence; and becauſe it is not handſome to exact money from Men for whom one has ſo ſtrange an Inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, I never ſpoke to him thereof, which was ſo pleaſing to him, that I had him at leaſt three times a Week at my Houſe, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch, that he made his Wife ſeveral times believe that he was obliged to go out of Town, that ſo he might come and ſpend thoſe Nights in my Company: To which I conſented as willingly, as if I had had for him the moſt violent Paſſion in the World.</p>
            <p>This familiar Frequentation had hardly laſted three months, when I perceived by all his Ways and Carriage that he began
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:106022:30"/>to be weary of me; which I might eaſily have prevented, if I had but ſome times denied him, and ſhewn ſome Repugnance to the Buſineſs: For it is certain, when we grant all things to men, without ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king any Reſiſtance, their Inclination will never be of long Continuance. On the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, a Refuſal done with Cunning and Artifice re-inflames their amorous Paſſions, and makes 'em laviſh all, ſo as they may but compaſs their Deſigns: For a Victory which is obtained without any Fatique, is not the moſt pleaſant and agreeable; and tho' they often do well enough ſee, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially if they be ſharpers and Cunning Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lants, that theſe Denyals are only coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeited, yet they will be a thouſand times more deſirous of the Embraces of thoſe Women, who knew how to behave them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with Art in that reſpect, than they are towards thoſe who like Hackneys, are always ready to let men mount upon them; but my Intention was not always to keep this Spark; and therefore I lived with him after a quite different manner, than I did with thoſe whom I only loved for Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit's ſake.</p>
            <pb n="58" facs="tcp:106022:31"/>
            <p>At firſt I complained very much of his Indifferency towards me; and reproached him, that he muſt of all neceſſity have to do with ſome other to whom he payed his Vows and Incenſe; and tho' the Oaths he made gave me ſufficiently to underſtand, that what I ſaid was not true, I could ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently comprehend, that he would not be over ſcrupulous at making his Addreſſes to another. As ſoon as I had made this Remarque, I thought it was time to put my Deſign in Execution: For that Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe I kept at my houſe for two days toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a very pretty Nymph, upon Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſhe would be faithful to me in all things: Whereupon I promiſed her a handſome Reward beſides what ſhe could obtain from him: When then that Alderman B— (ſo was the Name and Title of him for whom all theſe Preparations were made) came again to my houſe: He asked me, ſtrangely ſmitten, who that pretty Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture was; and if that Damoſel was to dwell with me? I told him yes, and that it was one of my Neeces, whom I had taken to keep me Company. To make ſhort, I pretended to have ſome Buſineſs to do a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad; and ſo pack'd out of the Room, that he might have an opportunity to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:106022:31"/>her, and he was ſo inflam'd in that Converſation, that when I came back a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove three hours after, I found him ſtill in her Company. At Night ſhe told me that he had courted her for you know what, but that according to my Order, ſhe had ſhowed her ſelf ſomewhat diſdainful, yet without making him loſe all hopes.</p>
            <p>The Alderman was much more paſſion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate for this Wench than for me, inſomuch that within the ſpace of a Week, he came ſix times to my Lodging; and during that time he had contracted ſuch a Familiarity with this <hi>Daughter</hi> of <hi>Venus,</hi> according to the opportunities that I had given them, that methought the time was come to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſh what I had projected to do where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon I one day told him, that three days afterwards I was to be at <hi>Windſor,</hi> and that I ſhould ſtay there a day or two. But that there might be the more probability in the Deſign of this Journey, I told him a Story which would really have required my Preſence of an abſolute Neceſſity. In the mean while I pretended to have ſome other Affairs in the Chamber where I lay, inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that the two Parties had the Leiſure to conclude their Bargain, as I had order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the matter, for the paſſing thoſe two
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:106022:32"/>Nights together that I was to be abſent. He proteſted, that ſhe ſhould meet with ſuch an Acknowledgment as ſhould be much more conſiderable than ſhe imagined; and that his words might find the better Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit, he had already let a Guiney ſlip down her Breaſt, becauſe the poor Innocent did really believe ſhe was a Virgin, or at leaſt that ſhe had been but very little uſed, tho' ſhe had maintained her ſelf for four years only by the labour of that Calling; and if we may believe the Teſtimonies of ſome brave Perſons, ſhe underſtood her ſelf bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in thoſe Affairs than can be expected from a Maiden as was but newly come out of her Parents Kitchin.</p>
            <p>When that the day appointed was come, I told my pretended Neece, that ſhe ſhould neither lock nor bolt the Door: For that I hoped to return home at twelve a Clock at Night, and that then I would teach her a way how to appropriate to our ſelves the Alderman's golden Purſe. Thereupon I departed; but not for <hi>Windſor:</hi> But went directly to an Officer in the Spiritual Court, and told him, that if he would give me a fourth part, as I was informed the Cuſtom was, I would deliver to him that Night a married Man, and a conſiderable Citizen,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:106022:32"/>from whom there would be a ſwinging Sum of Money to be got. This Officer was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently ready, and having given me his hand, he promiſed me that I ſhould have the half exactly. After which I told him who the Perſon was upon whom we were to exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute our Deſigns, as alſo his whole Eſtate, the Trade he drove, and all that was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, that ſo when he came to make the Agreement, he might not be too haſty to conclude the Bargain. Moreover, I told him, that about Midnight I would return to his houſe, to go afterwards both toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to mine, and ſurprize the Bird there in his Neſt.</p>
            <p>It had hardly ſtruck twelve when I got again to his Houſe which this Officer, who was a great Lover of Money, was no ſoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er informed of than that we began to ſet forwards on our way, and came at about half an hour paſt Twelve at my Houſe; where in we went ſo gently, that it was impoſſible for us to be heard: Then I lighted a Candle, and went up Stairs with the Officer, while that one of his Serjeants ſtaid in the Kitching, and the other at the Door. We found our Lovers lying folded in one anothers Arms, and repoſing ſo peaceably, that it ſeem'd almoſt Pity to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupt
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:106022:33"/>their Sleep. But as I have never been ſubject to a ſilly Compaſſion for men, I advanced towards the Bed-ſide; and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving pull'd him by the Arm ſo long as that he awaked. Mr. Alderman, ſaid I to him, if I had known you would have kept my houſe ſo well, I ſhould not have returned ſo ſoon. The Alderman rubbed his Eyes to diſſipate the Sleep, and ſeem'd very much amazed to hear my Voice; but he was much more ſurprized when the Officer told him, that he ſhould be his Priſoner for that time, if he pleaſed, ſince that ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a Wife in Marriage, he proceeded to have to do with another Woman. <hi>Jane,</hi> who in the mean while awaked upon this Noiſe, trembled for Amazement when ſhe ſaw this Officer before her: For ſhe knew not that I had done this Buſineſs with a ſet Deſign; and I had not declared it to her, for that I was not well enough aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that ſhe would be contented to go through with it; and beſides that, tho' ſhe had conſented to it, ſhe might have ſuffered her ſelf to be corrupted, and have diſcovered all to her Lover for a reaſonable Sum of Money: For there is no great Streſs to be laid upon the Words and Oaths of Wenches or Wives, who get their Living
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:106022:33"/>by their Bums. The Alderman not being ignorant that ſuch Affairs may be termina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by a Sum of Money, leap'd out of Bed as ſoon as he was ſomewhat recollected from his firſt Amazement, and deſired the Officer that he would allow him to ſpeak a word in private with him: Whereupon I went below Stairs with <hi>Jane,</hi> and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in a quarter of an hour, after there had been ſome Conteſt between them, I was called above with a Pen and Ink; and I ſaw the poor Devil, who ſigned a Bond of an hundred Pound, which he was to pay in a Fornights time. Thereupon the Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer was thinking of being gone, when that the Alderman, whoſe Fury ſparkled in his Eyes, would infallibly have broke my Neck; wherefore I deſired this honeſt Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman to take the Alderman along with him; and this laſt was forced to go along, tho' he would willingly have done ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what elſe. When they were out of the Door, I put a Letter into this unhappy Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver's Hands, wherein I related to him am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply with the moſt bitter words imaginable, for what reaſon I had ſerved him this Trick. I would couch that Letter here; but that I am afraid by reaſon of its Length, it would not give overmuch Satisfaction to thoſe
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:106022:34"/>ſhould read it. I ſhall deſiſt there from, and fill the Sheets I have ſtill left with ſome mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of more importance.</p>
            <p>Tho' poor <hi>Jenny</hi> had practiced this Trade, as long as is before mentioned, ſhe was ſo concerned at the Officers un-fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeen Preſence, and ſo much the more, as the ſhe had been found in Bed with a man, which is commonly rewarded with a <hi>Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well</hi> the Purgatory of Whores, that the day following ſhe was taken with a violent Fever, which moved me ſo to Compaſſion, by reaſon I could not deny but that I was the Cauſe thereof, that fifteen days after, having received my Part or Portion of the Booty, I gave her the half thereof, which was ſo powerful a Cordial and Remedy to that fair Damoſel in her Sickneſs, that in a ſhort time ſhe recovered her former Health and Beauty.</p>
            <p>Tho' this Action of Revenge had been very much to my Advantage, yet after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards I would have given more than I got by it, that I had managed the Affairs in ſuch a manner, as that he might have been ſeized on in another Houſe: For this Officer, who could gladly have wiſh'd, that I would from time to time have put a Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant of this kind into his hand began to be
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:106022:34"/>very troubleſome to me, inſomuch that he threatned me, that in caſe I did not do him other Services, he would make the Town too little for me. Wherefore for this Reaſon, and two others more, for I had heard my Husband was informed of the place of my Abode; and that he only ſought for an Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to have me catch'd by one or other, In the third place I was very much afraid the Alderman would ſet one or other to ſpie me by Night: Whereupon I found my ſelf obliged to decamp from the City, and to ſeek for my Abode out of its Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction: And in a few Days after I took a Houſe near <hi>Fulham,</hi> hard by the High Way that goes to <hi>Windſor;</hi> and went to dwell there with a Maid, making <hi>Jane</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that I was going for <hi>Norfolk:</hi> For as ſhe was young and beautiful, her Preſence would have cauſed too much Prejudice to my Commerce; and moreover I had alſo taken notice, that there were two more of my <hi>Gallants</hi> whom ſhe had ſupplanted me of. The Deſire of Revenge muſt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doubt have darkened my Eyes at that time: For I believe there is nothing more miſerable to ſee, than an Officer of Juſtice before our Eyes, upon whoſe Account we are oblig'd to trouble and diſturb honeſt
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:106022:35"/>People, when at the ſame time we would willingly keep our Friends; and indeed I ought to have had then the ſame thoughts; but as no body is always wiſe and pudent, I imagined that the Buſineſs would be done, but found quite the contrary: For thoſe Gentlemen reſemble Horſe-Leeches, and never leave ſucking their Prey, as long as they find the leaſt Humidity.</p>
            <p>But when I was entred with my Maid into my new Quarters, and had ſet all things in due Order, which kept me ſeveral days employed: For as I was a Damoſel of ſuch a Quality, I became ſomething coy and haughty. I compleated my Affairs ſo well, that I got to ſpeak with three or four of my beſt Gallants, to whom I made known in what place I had ſet up my Stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding: theſe did not in the leaſt fail to be there upon occaſion, which they might do with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any Apprehenſion: For indeed they had no reaſon to fear the Neighbours ſhould ſpie them: For I was in ſomewhat a ſolitary place, and for many days toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther I ſaw no body but my Maid and my Dog, which did not ill reſemble that <hi>Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berus</hi> the Poets ſo much talk of; the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly difference was, that my Dog had not three Heads like him.</p>
            <pb n="67" facs="tcp:106022:35"/>
            <p>Amongſt theſe Blades there was one who, after I had dwelt there for ſome time, brought with him a certain Spark of about thirty ſeven, or thirty eight years old, that he might be made Partaker of my Favors. At the firſt I pretended to be ſomewhat ſhy and ſcrupulous, neither more nor leſs than if I was not over deſirous that others ſhould come to ſee me; whereas, on the contrary, I could very well allow of all thoſe who made no difficulty to ſpend their Money: I grumbled at him who had brought this Stranger to my Houſe; but as this pettiſh Humor was only a Fiction, it did not laſt long; and within a few days this new comer was as welcome to me as the reſt: For the kindneſs he obtained from me was pretty dearly paid for: But after ſome weeks were paſt over, I percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved I had made a wrong Judgment, when I imagin'd, that in regard of Liberality, he was a man that did not yield in the leaſt to his Companions: For when he fancied, by reaſon I careſſed him ſo extreamly, that I was as much ſmitten with him as he was with me: He began to flatter himſelf that he was no longer bound to give me Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, and would willingly have obliged me to have diſcarded all the reſt, that he a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:106022:36"/>might have had the Enjoyment of my Perſon. I was extreamly diſpleaſed at this Carriage of his, yet let him not know it by the leaſt word; but I took a firm Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution, that upon the firſt opportunity I would play him a Pranck, which ſhould be ſufficient to furniſh my Maintenance for the ſpace of a Month.</p>
            <p>Do but, I beſeech you, take notice of the ingratitude that all theſe Men are guilty of: This fine Gallant had obtained of another the Favour of being brought to my Houſe; and as ſoon as his Crotchets had made him fancy, that he was pretty deeply rooted in my Heart, he would willingly have recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſed him to whom he had this Obligati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, by having him baniſhed from a houſe that he had frequented for ſo long a time. When I conſider well on all theſe things, I find my ſelf wholly amazed at the Diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der wherein Men have been for ſo many A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, when they have deſcribed the Vices under the Figure of Women, ſeeing the Men are therewith every where infected, I will ſay no more; but at leaſt as much as we, poor innocent Creatures as we are: For who would not be of my Opinion, that we ought to repreſent Pride as a young wanton Youth, ſince we ſee a number of
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:106022:36"/>thoſe Sparks ſwarm at preſent about <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> whoſe Bodies are ſtrait laced, that they may acquire a long and handſome Shape. And they not only amuſe themſelves in ſuch villainous Trifles; but I know ſome alſo, who, like women, make uſe of <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Paper to give a red Colour to their Cheeks: And thus beribbon'd, painted and curl'd, do theſe 'Squires ſtrut it about the Streets.</p>
            <p>I had a Deſign for at leaſt three Months together to make a Cully of <hi>Florian</hi> (for ſo was the name of this Gallant; or at leaſt ſo ſhall he here be called, before that I could ever find the Opportunity for ſo doing; and perhaps I might ſtill have waited a pretty while if he had not given it me himſelf; and behold after what manner: Coming one morning to my Houſe very early, he related to me, that he had ſome Affairs which obliged him to be at <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone</hi> for a day or two, having ſome Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandiſe to diſpoſe of there. He deſired me at the ſame time I would keep him Company in Quality of his Wife, without one moments Delay. I chuck'd him under the Chin, and embrac'd this poor man after a very amorous manner. You know very well my dear Angel, ſaid I to him, that I can refuſe you nothing, ſo ſtrong is the Love I
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:106022:37"/>bear you: Theſe words were followed with ſome Kiſſes, which inſinuated me ſo far into his good Opinion, that he did not in any wiſe doubt but that I was mortally ſmitten with Love for him.</p>
            <p>When we had attained to the day ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for our Journey, <hi>Florian</hi> came with a Hackney Coach to my Door, from whence we departed for <hi>Putney,</hi> and ſo to <hi>Kingſtone.</hi> where we took up our Inn near the Market Place: After we had refreſhed our ſelves with a Bit and a Glaſs, the Land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lady asked if ſhe ſhould make ready one or two Beds for us? We are very well con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented with one when we are at <hi>London,</hi> Landlady, anſwered my Servant; and by conſequence there needs no more here. Thus the poor Woman, thinking we were married together, garniſhed but one Bed, which wemade ſo hard that night with our petulant Members, that it leſs reſembled a Feather-Bed than a Seaman's Quilt. The Day after <hi>Florian</hi> went out to diſpatch his Buſineſs, and received about fifty or three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcore Pounds. While we were upon the way, he had informed me of all his Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs as amply as was requiſite for the bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing about my Enterprize. Thus he came about Noon to our Inn, and having given
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:106022:37"/>his money to the Landlord to keep, we went to Dinner, and ſpent the reſt of the day in ſeeing the Town; But my good or malicious Reader, for I know not which I have to doe with, not to importune you any longer with a great number of Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, know that after my Lover was gone out the next morning, I ſent for a Silk-Mercer that was there in Town, and having bought of his goods, as much as came to ten pounds, I deſired the Landlord to give me my Husband's bag of money; he imagining that it was the ſame thing whether he gave it to me or to <hi>Florion,</hi> made not the leaſt difficulty in the buſineſs. Whereupon I made uſe of the money to pay that Mercer, and delivered the reſt to the Landlord to lock up again, for my In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention was not to deprive him of all the ſum, tho' I might have done it very eaſily if I had not been afraid of ſome ill conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence; but I only deſigned to be paid for the uſe of my Body, and as he had not had the Civility to do it, I thought I ſhould have been a very great fool if I had not made uſe of the power I had in hand. Poor <hi>Florion</hi> was no ſooner returned to the Inn than that he asked me with a meen full of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoniſhment to whom that Silk belonged, or
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:106022:38"/>I was ſo buſie with it that he could eaſily perceive I had ſome concern therein. It belongs to us, my dear heart, anſwered I him in the preſence of the Inkeeper and his Wife; you know you promiſed me a new Gown a long while ago: <hi>Florion</hi> became as pale as Death, and having asked me with what I had payed for it, I told him the truth, inſomuch that he could hardly for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear unravelling the whole Myſtery, ſo vex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed was he at this loſs which he had not in the leaſt expected. He called me aſide, told me that it was not handſomely done to make uſe of his money as if it had been my own without firſt knowing if it was his will and pleaſure ſo to have it, and I ought firſt to have inquired if he ſhould not have ſtood in need of it himſelf at <hi>Kingſtone.</hi> How, Sir, ſaid I to him, as ſoon as he had done ſpeaking you ſhall notneed to be much concerned for your money, ſince as ſoon as we are got back to <hi>London,</hi> I will repay it you every farthing. And that you may not think that theſe are only vain words I will give you a Bond immediately for the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of what I ſay. I ſhould never as long as I live have any good luck in a Gown, ſaid I ſtill, that was given me ſo unwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly.</p>
            <pb n="73" facs="tcp:106022:38"/>
            <p>Thereupon I called for a Pen and Ink. But <hi>Florion</hi> in his turn would needs act the Generous Man, becauſe he fancyed that I had taken his procedure in very ill part, and was by conſequence afraid he ſhould be put out of my favour. Whereupon he ſei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed me by the Arm, ſaying, that for the money that was no great matter, but that he had thought to have had made uſe of it himſelf, and that it had fallen out very un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luckily, that I had taken ſo great a quanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of it, but nevertheleſs he knew how to provide againſt that Inconveniency; thus perceiving that this piece of cunning had ſucceeded well with me, I put my ſelf in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a much more haughty poſture, and would needs by all means give him a Bond, tho' I had not the leaſt thought of reſtoring to him one farthing of his money, but it became me to carry high as if it was to ſhow that I had an honorable Education, and that I ſtood in no need of money, inſomuch that <hi>Florion</hi> ſeeing me, ſo out of humour, made uſe of all manner of flatteries to regain my Affection; imagining without doubt that for this money he ſhould take his pleaſures with me for a pretty while; but the poor man did not think that I made quite an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther account; for it came into my Head
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:106022:39"/>that we were then but two at play, and that if he meant to receive new favours, it was eaſie for him to judge that it was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for him to ſhow new money, which preſently after I gave him ſo well to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand by new tricks and Artifices, that at length my Amorous Careſſes ſeem'd too dear to him; Inſomuch that he began to wean himſelf from me by little and little, for then he could eaſily ſee that it was not his Perſon but his money that I loved, and that I had only let him be free-coſt ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times that I might make him pay the dearer for my Merchandiſe.</p>
            <p>Without lying I cannot forbear laughing when I think on thoſe poor innocent Cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, who ſeeing themſelves flattered and careſſed by ſuch a Nymph as I was at that time, imagine, when we do not ſpeak to them of money every Bout, that they are the only Men who enjoy our Favour and Affection: Whereas on the contrary it is certain they may haunt Miſſes at a much cheaper Rate, when they know how they muſt pay every time, than thoſe who have the Fancy, that they are the well-beloved, by reaſon they never hear 'em ſpeak of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward or recompence: For theſe Miſſes al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways ſtand in need of ſomething; and if
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:106022:39"/>one would have the enjoyment of their Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, you cannot be ſo uncivil, unleſs you have a mind to loſe that counterfeited kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, to refuſe them the Favours they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand; ſo much the more, as that theſe demands are accompanied with ſo many Kiſſes and Careſſes, that it is hardly poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to refuſe them; and thoſe things are commonly ſo dearly ſold, that the ſame Price would often buy Diamonds and Jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els; Here perhaps might an Objection be ſtarted, that theſe Miſſes are as ſenſible to love as others; and that by Conſequence I do not eſtabliſh my Opinion ſtrong e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, and perhaps ſome examples might be alledged to the Contrary; but theſe Sparks who are of this ſentiment, may be pleaſed to know, that we ſeldome ſee thoſe things done with ſincerity, beſides as that it is impoſſible to ſound the Heart of a Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man ſo as to lay any Foundation thereupon, and that there are thoſe of that nature that when they ſeem to bear you the greateſt love in the World, they hate you more than the Pleague at the bottom of their Hearts, and they only give you Teſtimonies of their good will to fleece you of your Wool, which you have no ſooner loſt, than that you will find, that you will be treated
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:106022:40"/>after the ſame rate as a Prodigal Child. However I can eaſily perſwade my ſelf that a Miſs who gets her livelyhood with her back Cheeks may grow enamoured, but yet I cannot believe that ſhe will place her Incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation upon one man who is of an Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable breeding, and of a reaſonable Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation, and eſpecially at this time, when thoſe who ſeek their maintenance in this commerce are Daughters of Orenge Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men and the <hi>Billingsgate</hi>-crew, and by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence of a vile and baſe Education; theſe having bought a Gown or a Manteau which they find here and there in the Shops paſs for Miſſes, and are imployed in that quality by one or other; but as their ſorry Educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion had uſed them to all manner of ill car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage and behaviour, and as by getting on a Gown and by ſprucing themſelves up fine they do not ſhake off thoſe effects which are rooted in their Hearts, you muſt never expect that they will come to caſt their Eyes upon a man of extraction, but upon ſome Clown or Bumpking whoſe Inſide manners ſuit better with theirs; for it is a truth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond all conteſt that the conformity of paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions and courſes of living do engender the greateſt love, whereas I could here urge ſeveral examples if I had a mind to't, but
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:106022:40"/>ſince that thoſe Brutal paſſions do not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the Name of love, I ſhall advance in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to other matters, and leave every one the freedome to have the opinion and belief he thinks beſt.</p>
            <p>By this way of dealing, I mean by ſcra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping up money from Sparks by all imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable means, I now and then loſt one of thoſe whoſe Means were not ſufficient nor rich enough to reſiſt the inſatiable avidity of my love towards money. Perhaps you will here think, my Reader, that I could not loſe many Gallants, ſince I had already ſaid that their number did but conſiſt in three or four; but be pleaſed to know that this num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber did ſo wonderfully encreaſe in a year or two, that I could well ſpare ſome without remaining ſo deſtitute of Servants as Miſſes often do at preſent. What contributed very much to my happyneſs was, that then I did not ſhew my ſelf ſo coy, ſo nice and ſcrupulous, for as I perceived that my Beauty and Youth began to periſh by little and little, and that by conſequence I fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaw that in the ſequel of time I ſhould not be ſo paſſionately nor ſo frequently ſought after, I made uſe of all manner of diligence to provide for my ſelf againſt Old Age that I might not be obliged to beg Alms.</p>
            <pb n="78" facs="tcp:106022:41"/>
            <p>Amongſt thoſe whom my Charms capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vated under my Laws, there was an <hi>Italian</hi> of about thirty years of Age, and in whoſe Perſon I had had a very good Gallant; for I never asked of him any thing but what he immediately gave me. But if I had known the <hi>Italians</hi> could have practiſed ſo great a diſſimulation as they are uſed to do, I ſhould have been much more cauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous of him, tho' however I ought not to take the thing ſo very ill; for as it was my cuſtome to deceive others, and as I ſhould not have taken delight in ſeeing that men had been wanting to treat me with all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of reſpect and civility, methinks it is but juſt, likewiſe, that I forget what has been done to me, to which I find my ſelf obliged with ſo much the more reaſon, as that I cannot ſay, that he ſtole from me more than I had got from him before. Yet it might well be that I ſhould not ſpeak ſo much of forgetting that pranck, if I had only the opportunity to pay him in the ſame Coyn, but by reaſon he returned to his own Country, he deprived me of the means of ſatisfying my deſire of Revenge, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe it ſhould have been a wonderful Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digy if I had been of ſo ſedate a temper to be ſerved ſuch a trick; or I muſt at leaſt have
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:106022:41"/>loſt the whole nature of the Female Sex; for this paſſion, namely the deſire of revenge, takes its Birth jointly with the Females, and remain with them until that they have given up the laſt Gaſp. But not to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maze our ſelves too long, I am going to tell you the whole matter.</p>
            <p>He had frequented me for about half a year when that we took a journey together to <hi>Graveſend</hi> whither he ſaid he was to go by reaſon a Ship was arrived there from <hi>Holland</hi> wherein he expected ſome Cloaths; on the morrow morning after we had lain together and enjoyed to our full the delights of love, he took my Pendants into his hand, for which my Husband had given forty pounds, and having conſidered them with great ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culation, they are ſomething too plain ſaid he to me with a ſmiling Countenance, for a fair Creature to whom I bear ſo much af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, and thereupon calling the Land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lord up into our Room, he asked him if he had not any acquaintance with ſome Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weller who could fit up a pair of fine Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants, the man made anſwer he had, and added that there was a Jeweller who fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quented his Houſe from whom he might buy what he deſired for as reaſonable a price as of any other Merchant about <hi>London,</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="80" facs="tcp:106022:42"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Jukomo</hi> (ſo was the <hi>Italians</hi> name) deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red him, immediately that he might be ſent for, which was accordingly inſtantly performed; in the mean while I was ſo over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed that my joy was apparent in my Eyes; for I expected no leſs then the value of ſix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty or ſeventy pounds, and I had ſtill more hopes when I heard this deceitful <hi>Italian</hi> tell the Jeweller, that none of the Pendants he had brought along with him pleaſed him, tho' there were ſome perhaps worth four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcore pounds. Sir, anſwered the other, I have of all prizes, and if you pleaſe to take the pains to go along with me to my Houſe, I do not doubt but that we ſhall agree upon the matter. I would willingly have gone along with them, but <hi>Jakomo</hi> would not conſent to that, which made me fancy that he deſigned to make me a better Preſent than I expected. I had had this in my imagination for about half an hour, when that the Jeweller came back to our Inn to ask me for the Pendants which the <hi>Italian</hi> had undoubtedly left me only ſo long that I might ſo much the leſs perceive the deſign he had. I asked him what he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to do with them, and if they ſhould have concluded the Bargain. It is only Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, to ſee the bigneſs of them, who took
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:106022:42"/>me without doubt for a Woman of great Quality, and as for what concerns the Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, perſued he, your Husband has offered me money for a pair, but he muſt ſtill raiſe the Sum he offers. Yes, ſaid I, but I hope you'l uſe him kindly. And thereupon I took off my Pendants, and wrapped them in a piece of Paper, and delivered them to him without any ill ſuſpicion, ſince he came himſelf in Perſon to receive them, for to have confided them to any other, I ſhould have made ſome ſcruple.</p>
            <p>In the mean while, I expected ſome joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Tydings, but my Husband came not back to our Lodging. Yet I durſt not at firſt ſeem to be uneaſy, though my heart miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gave me ſtrangely; but when it was paſt twelve, and that I ſaw no Body yet come back, I deſired my Landlord that he would lead me to the Jewellers Houſe; where I was no ſooner come, than that he told me they could not agree upon the matter, for that my Husband, ſaid the Jeweller to me, had only offered for a pair of Pendants, ſixty pounds, which had coſt him above Eighty.</p>
            <pb n="82" facs="tcp:106022:43"/>
            <p>I preſently asked him what were become of mine; and having had for anſwer, that my Husband had taken them along with him, my Heart was as much troubled as if I had been ſeized with a violent Fever: Yet I durſt not let any Sign thereof appear, both for that the Inkeeper was with me, and that we had lain together in his Houſe, as if we had been Man and Wife: So that it would have been very improper to, have made a hurry for my Jewels, ſince that they had been put into my Husband's hands, or at leaſt in his who was taken to be ſo; and on the other ſide, I had no reaſon ſince I had not forbid the Jeweller to give them to any other than my ſelf. Thus we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned to the Inn, and though I ought to have been well aſſured, that I ſhould never ſee the Pendants or the <hi>Italian</hi> again, yet I continued to flatter my ſelf a long time with ſuch hopes, that he was perhaps, gone to ſome other Jewellers Houſe: But at length ſeeing he came not home again at Night, I loſt all Courage, my Tears guſht out in Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents accompanied with Sobs, while that my Landlady kept me Company, which ſhe would undoubtedly have ſpared her ſelf the trouble of, if ſhe had known for what rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon I afflicted my ſelf in that manner; but
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:106022:43"/>the Poor Woman imagined, that if I ſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandoned my ſelf to Sadneſs, it was for no other reaſon than for the abſence of my Husband, to whom ſhe fancied ſome Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chance had happened. I ſtayed ſome days ſtill at <hi>Graveſend,</hi> as a Perſon void of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, as you may well think, and I ran through all parts of the Town inquiring af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter my Husband, in all the Inns and Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verns, where I thought that he might be gone, but the Bird was already flown, ſo that I was at length conſtrained to return to my own Home. Being in the Boat, I i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magined that I might eaſily come to the knowledge of the place of his Abode, by the means of the Perſon who brought him firſt of all to our Houſe, and ſo get again what I had loſt. I did not delay in the leaſt to make uſe of this Way; but afterwards I wiſh'd heartily that this Thought had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver come into my head; for as ſoon as I had found out his Lodging, and had conceived ſome good hopes, I ſaw my ſelf forced to renew my affliction, becauſe his Landlord told me, that he had taken his leave of him four or five days before, to go to <hi>Graveſend</hi> and ſo into <hi>Holland,</hi> where he ſaid, he had ſome buſineſs, and that from thence he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to return into <hi>Italy.</hi> I plainly conje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctured
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:106022:44"/>from this Anſwer, that I was to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain no more hopes of ever recovering my Pendants again; wherefore from that very Moment I uſed all my Endeavours to ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh them from my Memory, tho' that it was not without a great deal of trouble; but time which makes all things forgotten, brought ſome Moderation to my Sadneſs; and perhaps, I ſhould have almoſt loſt all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance thereof, if it did not ſpight me to this very day, that I accompanied him ſo far.</p>
            <p>How great ſoever my grief and trouble was, I durſt not complain to any Body of the loſs I had had, fearing I ſhould be laught at, and the remembrance thereof was ſtill very freſh, when I drew into my Snares an Old Seignior, of whom I got in a little time as much as was neceſſary to repair the dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage I had received, for it is an inconteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble truth, that thoſe who have paſſed the Age of Fifty Years, are much more eaſy to diſburſe Money than thoſe who are between twenty and forty, for theſe imagine, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they rarely want Strength and Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour, that they are not obliged to give mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, or at leaſt that they ought not to give much, whereas on the contrary, the others willingly recompence for their Impotence
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:106022:44"/>with Caſh, and are ordinarily ſo careful of their Reputation, that there is no fear of their Vifits cauſing Scandalous Reports; but becauſe Accidents equally rare, do not happen to all manner of Perſons, though I could eaſily fill this Piece with Adventures and Rencounters, altogether wonderful, if I would in the leaſt paſs the bounds of truth, I ſhall only ſay this of that good Man, that I proſpered very well by his frequenting my Company; and that I hardly ever deman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded any thing of him but what he gave me immediately; inſomuch, that during ten or eleven Months, that he haunted me, I heap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up as much Money as was neceſſary to defend me againſt the Injuries of a ſharp and ſevere Winter.</p>
            <p>About two or three Months after the Death of this Honeſt Gentleman, I was one day ſitting upon a little Seat before my Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, and from thence I heard a moſt ſad and doleful Cry at ſome diſtance. I turned immediately my eyes towards the place from whence that voice came, and I ſaw a Middle-Aged Woman dreſſed like a Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen's Wife, who came running towards me with all her Strength, being perſued by two Furious Men, who had each of them a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked Sword in his hand. I got up, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:106022:45"/>into the Garden, that I might not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive any offence from thoſe <hi>Furioſo's;</hi> but I had hardly ſet my foot over the Treſhold when the Woman, who it ſeems was ligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of foot than thoſe who perſued her, came flying to me, and ſhutting the Door with a trembling hand, for the <hi>Love of God,</hi> Madam, ſaid ſhe, <hi>ſave my Life,</hi> for thoſe two Men.—She would ſtill have ſaid more, but her wearineſs and weakneſs would not allow of it.</p>
            <p>In the mean while, thoſe two Men muſt either have been gone back, or muſt have hid themſelves ſomewhere: For as ſoon as the Woman was got into the Garden I heard no more Noiſe. I call'd my Maid, and having made her fetch a Bottle of Wine, I gave this damnable Creature to drink, conſidering her as a good and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Woman, and ſo I comforted her heart. Then we went into our Houſe, where I ask'd her for what cauſe thoſe two Rogues had purſued her with ſo much Fury? Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, if I was aſſured, ſaid ſhe to me, that we could talk here, without any Body hearing us, I ſhould undertake to relate to you a Story which you will be extreamly ſurprized at; and tho' I have been in ſuch Danger as you know, I would never open
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:106022:45"/>my Mouth of it; but by reaſon of the ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable help which I have received from you, I will undertake to relate to you a Story which will extreamly ſurprize you; and tho' I have been in the danger you ſaw, will never open my Mouth thereof; but upon the account of the ſeaſonable help which I have received from you, the duty of Acknowledgment obliges me not to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe you any thing: For thoſe Men whoſe Bloody Hands purſued me, and from whom your Goodneſs has delivered me, are ſo nearly related to me, that I cannot make any Complaints againſt 'em, without draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon my ſelf the hatred of all my Race. I told her thereupon, by reaſon that this Introduction did very much aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment my Curioſity, that ſhe might ſpeak with all manner of Safety, that there were but we three in the Houſe; and that my Maid was too wiſe and ſecret to go cackle abroad what ſhe ought to keep in Silence. As ſoon as I had utter'd theſe Words, ſhe fell to telling a Story, which ſeem'd as if it would never have been at an end, inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that I began to conceive ſome Suſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picion, that this was only the Pretext to ſome concealed Deſign. I had ſo much the more reaſon to be jealous, that tho'
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:106022:46"/>this Story was told after a pertinent man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner enough, yet there was ſuch prodigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and ſuch Romantick Circumſtances, that it could not be taken to be made up altogether of pure Truths; and particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly amongſt perſons who have ſomewhat more Underſtanding than what's common in the World. Whereupon I told her, that her entertaining Story had laſted for above three quarters of an hour, and that it was time to make an end, by reaſon, that it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing near Eight a Clock, it would be late before ſhe could get to Town. But, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, ſaid ſhe, I hope you will not be ſo pitileſs as to refuſe me a Lodging this night; for I am ſure, purſued this Bitch, that my Enemies will wait for me hereabouts. You muſt not take it ill tho' I do, Good Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, replied I, my Husband is not at home, and for that reaſon <hi>I</hi> cannot allow any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther perſon to lie at my Houſe. <hi>I</hi> added ſeveral other reaſons more of the like Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture (for <hi>I</hi> began to dread ſome ill Event of this Enterprize) ſo that at length ſhe told me, ſince that you make ſo much dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty in this Matter, <hi>I</hi> will abridge my Diſcourſe, and ſhew you a Letter, wherein you may learn all things you ſtand in need of for the Abridgement of my Buſineſs.
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:106022:46"/>Thereupon feeling in her Pocket, ſhe took out a Letter which <hi>I</hi> quickly knew again, and which ſet me a trembling and ſhiver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing after ſo terrible a manner, as if <hi>I</hi> had fallen into a Convulſion Fit: For it was the ſame <hi>I</hi> had put into the Rope-Dancer's Hands when <hi>I</hi> ſent him to <hi>Thiſtleworth</hi> in ſuch an Equipage as was deſcribed in the Firſt Part of this Book.</p>
            <p>While I was reading this Letter, and that I ſeem'd to dwell upon it with the higheſt Attention, I conſidered ſo well this counterfeited Woman, that at length, tho' it was a long time ſince, and that his Cloaths were very different from thoſe he was uſed to wear, I knew again the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of that abominable Thief, who had cauſed his Face to be ſhaved very ſmooth. Hereupon ſome one might tell me that there needed no more than to hear his Voice to perceive that it was a Cheat; but that of this Rogue was none of the deepeſt, inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that liſping and affecting a little of the Tone of the Female Sex, he might paſs for a Woman of a middle Age. After that I had held this Letter for a pretty while, with trembling hands I delivered it to him without having almoſt the Power to utter <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> word but in Stuttering. Well, my
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:106022:47"/>dear Angel, ſaid the Rogue, with a ſmiling Countenance, have not I ſpoke the Truth, and can you not eaſily perceive by this Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, all that my Buſineſs requires to have the perfect Underſtanding thereof? I made him Anſwer with a ſtuttering Tongue, that I knew not what he meant by that Letter, by reaſon that it was not at all conformable to the Story he had related; and that by Conſequence he muſt have taken one Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for another. However I am very well aſſured, replied he after a haſty manner, that you know well enough the Perſon to whom that Letter was written; and not to trouble our Heads with impertinent diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes, added he, know that I am the Man whom you ſent in a Boat to <hi>Thiſtle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worth;</hi> and that there was no other reaſon that made me keep this Letter ſo long than to convict you of that curſed Pranck by your own hand writing. Do not believe, purſued he, that I have forgot your Face: For Spite and Vexation have ſo deeply imprinted it in my Heart, that it would be eternally ineffaceable. My Maid, to whom I had related this Story, look'd upon me fixedly, with Eyes full of Sadneſs: For ſhe certainly foreſaw that this would not paſs thus without ſome hurry and miſchief:
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:106022:47"/>nevertheleſs I ſtill pretended to be ignorant of the matter; and told him, that I knew not what he meant by all his Diſcourſe, and that I could not imagine what he preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to do, in ſhaping himſelf ſometimes in the Poſture of a Woman, and ſometimes in that of a Man. I will then make uſe of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther means, and taking at the ſame time out of his Pocket a Knife prodigiouſly long, Come, you Whore, ſaid he to me, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce me immediately that Money thou tookeſt from me at that time, and my Cloaths alſo, with the Intereſt of ſo many years that have paſſed ſince; or immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately prepare thy ſelf for Death. <hi>I</hi> ſtarted up as ſoon as ever <hi>I</hi> ſaw the naked Knife, and thought to have got out at the Garden Door, to have Recourſe to crying and bawling out for Help; but ſeizing on me, he put the Knife to my Throat, ſwearing he would run it in, if <hi>I</hi> made the leaſt Noiſe. Thus knew not <hi>I</hi> what to do in this Extremity: For tho' <hi>I</hi> did my beſt to perſwade him that he was miſtaken, my words found no Credit; and having no Deſign to rid my ſelf of ſo much Money, <hi>I</hi> imagin'd that there was no better means to rid my ſelf of this Misfortune, than to confeſs the thing, and endeavour to make
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:106022:48"/>him believe, that all <hi>I</hi> had done had only been through my Mothers Counſels, and afterwards to Careſs him to ſuch a degree, that his Coller might be at length appeaſed; but theſe means were all to no purpoſe, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch that <hi>I</hi> ſhould then have been obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to have given him as much and perhaps more Money, if <hi>I</hi> intended to preſerve my life, which however would not have been the leſs in danger, when that of a ſudden <hi>I</hi> heard a noiſe that was made by beating up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon a Braſs Kettle from the Top of our Garret, and ſuch a terrible crying out of Murder, that all the Houſe rung again. This Rural Alarum was given by my-Maid, who, while the Rope-Dancer was holding his Knife at my Throat, had ſtole up Stairs. God damn you, you execrable Whore you, ſaid this Bloody Villain, as ſoon as he had heard this Sound and this Voice, thou ſhalt not come off however ſo cheaply; and thereupon ſhutting the Door, that <hi>I</hi> might not make my Eſcape, he ran up above; but the Maid had had the Prudence to pull up the Ladder after her, ſo that he could not do her any Miſchief.</p>
            <p>In the mean while, having opened one of our Windows, and being got out there <hi>I</hi> ſet our Dog at Liberty, flattering my
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:106022:48"/>ſelf, that <hi>I</hi> was then ſufficiently ſecur'd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all Misfortune: For that Animal was prodigiouſly big, and would eaſily have torn to pieces two or three men; and by Conſequence this Devil of a Murderer, if he had not been too cunning for him: for he no ſooner perceiv'd that the Dog came in all haſte towards him, than that he ſtretched forth his left Arm, and the Dog planted his Teeth therein immediately. Now as my <hi>Cerberus</hi> ſtood upright, and had his Fore-Feet againſt his Arm, he cut open all his Belly at one Slaſh with the Knife he had in the other, inſomuch that the poor Creature fell upon the Ground, having ſtill Life enough to ſee his own En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trails drop out; and tho' ſeveral People came to my help from the Houſes there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abouts, as we could ſufficiently perceive by the Noiſe they made, yet he purſued me ſo faſt, and came ſo near me, that ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king at me, he cut me over the Head, by which I could paſs no other Judgment than that he intended to cut my Throat: And to make him believe that he had done my Buſineſs already, and to prevent any farther Miſchief from him (for I had alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy perceived that my running away was all to no purpoſe, I fell topſy turvy upon
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:106022:49"/>the Ground, without uttering one word. As ſoon as he had committed this abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Action, he let fall his Robes, under which was his Nuns Cloaths; and having got in a Moment to the Pails, which he mounted over, and ſo skudded away like a Hare, with ſuch Swiftneſs, that he made a ſhift to eſcape before People could come in. By theſe means he made me loſe the Pleaſure I ſhould have had in ſeeing him up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a Gallows. As ſoon as People ſaw the Condition I was in, they carried me to <hi>Fulham,</hi> where I had my Wound bound up for the firſt time.</p>
            <p>The day following a Juſtice of the Peace came to inquire into the buſineſs, I gave him a very pertinent account, except that I did not declare to him the cauſe for which that fatal accident had happened to me. But not to trouble the Reader with circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of ſmall importance, I will only ſay that this fact was taken for a piece of robbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and by conſequence all manner of dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence was uſed to find out the Authors thereof, but all in vain.</p>
            <p>For my part, tho' I was ſo bravely mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked yet I thought my ſelf happy in my miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortune, for if I had kept him a night at my Houſe, he would infallibly have robbed me
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:106022:49"/>of all that I had in the night, and perhaps he would have marked me ten times as much, if he had not broke my Neck. It is not to be doubted but that the Devil him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf inſpired him with this deſign, and had made him find out the place of my abode, for I cannot imagine how he could have diſcovered it, for I was very rarely to be ſeen abroad, by reaſon I was very much a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid of my Husband and the Alderman, tho' it ſeemed as if by the length of time thoſe Sparks had forgotten the miſchief I had done them; for as for my Husband I had nothing to fear from him, by reaſon that I would not in any wiſe own that I had been his Wife; and touching the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derman, that unlucky adventure had ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred him ſo Virtuous, that he no longer thought of me nor ſuch like Perſons; from whence I draw a ſure conſequence that he was obliged to me, and that therefore he would have done very ill, had he done me any miſchief, becauſe he might look upon me as the occaſion of his Virtuous Life. Here it might be objected, that we muſt never do any miſchief that good may come thereof, but my Maximes were who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly different from this, and I was very little concerned whether they were conformable
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:106022:50"/>or not with the Prophane or holy Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy.</p>
            <p>But being half cured of this wound which I ſhould not perhaps have received, if after having let looſe the Dog in the Garden, I had immediately made uſe of my Heeles; but I was willing to have the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of ſeeing that Battail, wherein I did not doubt but that my <hi>Cerberus</hi> would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main the Conquerour, I went to take my Habitation again in the Town, by reaſon I was in ſear that ſuch like misfortunes might again happen to me; but tho' there Chirur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geons had me in cure, it was not however ſo well cured but that my Forehead re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main'd ſcarrified and ſpoiled, becauſe the ſcarrs continued ſo viſible, that they might have been perceived a Muskets-ſhot diſtance, Inſomuch that ſince that time, I have been always obliged to wear Cornets, and my Forehead-wear of very thick Laces, that this imperfection might not be ſeen through the holes. At firſt by reaſon I had a very fine Fore-head, I have ſhed many a tear up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that account, but afterwards cuſtome became nature, with ſo much the more rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that I came to conſider that there are many others, who for that they have an ill
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:106022:50"/>ſhaped Forehead, are obliged to dreſs them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in this manner, for certainly it is not allways to follow the Mode that Women wear Cornets; but it is moſt commonly to hide the imperfections of the Forehead; neverthleſs I ſhould yet have been happy if I had been quit for that; but I had not dwelt full a year in the City, then that my Face, my Hands and all my Body became ſo yellow, by having been too often at the ſport, that one would have ſaid I had dwelt five or ſix years under the Equinocti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Line, ſo that I was conſtrained to make uſe not only of <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Paper, but alſo of Paint, unleſs I intended to loſe my Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merſe I would make here the deſcription, after what manner it is uſed, as I have done in the former part touching the Red Colour that is given to the Cheeks; but becauſe there are ſo many ſeveral ſorts of paint, and that this artifice is become very common in our time, perhaps the pains I ſhould take would be very little to the purpoſe; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, I have an other reaſon for which I am not willing to engage in this matter, which is, that <hi>I</hi> ſhould ſtand in need of ten times as much Paper as is fitting for the bulk of this Book to be, if <hi>I</hi> would relate here all the practiſes which the Female Sex makes uſe of to help nature, and tho' <hi>I</hi> ſhould ſay
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:106022:51"/>nothing but what is conformable to truth, yet perhaps <hi>I</hi> ſhould not always be allowed of as an infallible Author; for they practiſe ſo many ſtrange things in this matter, that they ſeem at firſt abſolutely incredible. By example. Who would believe if experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence did not baniſh all Contradiction, that there are young Women who faſten Ropes to the top of their Beds, or ſome other thing, where lying on their Backs, they thruſt their Hands therein? And this is done only that the Blood may retire, and they ſeem the whiter: And for that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe they muſt endure the Pennance of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuing lying in that manner for a whole night together without being able to turn on the one ſide or other: But I ſhall add here to ſomething more ſurprizing, which is, that as there have been ſome who having Warts, Freckles, or ſome ſuch other like Deformities in their Faces, have taken off the Skin with biting Waters and ſuch other like means, for the recovering a new Skin which might not be ſubject to be disfigured like the former. I am willing to believe that there are many Maidens to whom this will ſeem incredible, and particularly to thoſe who have yet but very little experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and who have always been kept un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:106022:51"/>the laſh of their Parents, yet it is as true as that we may with our Eyes diſcern the light and darkneſs: But this point has been ſufficiently talked of, and methinks I hear ſome of thoſe proud Creatures ſaying, that I ought to be burnt alive, becauſe I ſo clearly reveal their ſecrets; but I am ſo little concerned at all their murmurings, that if I was reſolved to ſpoil more Paper, I would tell a thouſand things more which I now paſs under ſilence. There is no other reaſon which witholds me from ſo doing, but that I find my ſelf weary of writing of Books. Yet people muſt not however ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin, that I am too great an Enemy of the Female Sex, on the contrary I know very well that my duty engages me to bear it affection: But at preſent I hate all manner of diſſimulation, and am in love with no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſo much as plain dealing.</p>
            <p>Thus when I had dwelt about a year and half in the City, I had the adventure of making acquaintance with a certain Spark who was newly come from the <hi>Eaſt-Indies</hi> in the quality of a Merchant, and who, as is the cuſtome of thoſe Gentlemen, had brought along with him ſo much rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, that he might well enough ſpend the
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:106022:52"/>reſt of his Life without putting himſelf to the Peril of going ſuch an other Voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age.</p>
            <p>As ſoon as I was informed hereof by him who had had the goodneſs to bring him to my Houſe, I put all manner of tricks and ſtratagems in practice to get part of his riches. The truth is, I ſucceeded reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nably well in this deſign; but I was for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to do and ſuffer more for him, than I had ever done for any other; for he had the Imperfection common to all thoſe who come from that Countrey, which is, that he was of a very Brutiſh humour, and very ſubject to jealouſy, that I could hardly paſs an hour in peace with him, tho' for his money I ſhow'd him ten times more kindneſs than I ſhould have done in my tender Youth.</p>
            <p>But it was now quite another thing; for ſince my age was encreaſed, and that my Beauty was diminiſhed, I had loſt from time to time ſome or other of my Gallants, Inſomuch that I found my ſelf conſtrained, if I meant to ſatisfie my inſatiable deſire of heaping up money, to endure much more than I was uſed to do before. And indeed
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:106022:52"/>I became at length ſo audacious that he of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten threatned me to make me feel the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vyneſs of his Cane, and if I would have played the Beaſt, his threatnings would un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly have been followed with Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as I found afterwards by experience that he was no Man that lyed of his word: Tho' I then gained great profit by my com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce with him, yet I took this in terrible Dudgeon, and moreover took a firm Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution to hinder his ever coming to thoſe extremities, or at leaſt to do on my ſide all that was poſſible for me, to which purpoſe, in a little time a very fair oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity was offered.</p>
            <p>One evening he came to my Houſe where he found a Gentleman ſitting by me, with whom I had had Frequentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a long while before his coming. He told me after a ſurly manner that he did not intend I ſhould render my ſelf ſo familiar with others, and that he had connived at it for a conſiderable time; but that henceforward he would prevent it, ſince he furniſhed me with ſufficient to live upon. Very well, Cavalier, ſaid I to him, perhaps you fancy you are ſtill in the <hi>Indies,</hi> and that you have one of
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:106022:53"/>your ſlaviſh Wives. How long is it ſince you bought me, added I, ſince you arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate ſo much Authority over me? Since I kiſſed you the firſt time, reparteed <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ximus</hi> (ſo was his name) with a dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful look, and ſince I have given you your livelyhood. Well you ſcoundrel, ſaid I to him (for I could no longer diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſeeing he affronted me ſo villainouſly in the preſence of an other, I never let my ſelf be kiſs'd yet by ſuch Aſſes as you are, and I hope I ſhall never have the thought of having acquaintance with ſuch a Beaſt.</p>
            <p>I had hardly uttered theſe words than that he applyed to me two very fine Boxes of the Ear, which were followed with three or four ſwinging Strapadoes of the Cane, with a Garniſh of about a dozen injurious words. I ran immediately to the Bed, where there was a Chamber-Pot, wherein I had cacked ſeven or eight times, for I had taken Pills that morning to purge my Body a little; and having run in both my Hands, I caſt it upon <hi>Maximus</hi>'s Breaſt with all the Strength and Fury of an enraged Woman, inſomuch that the Pieces which were none of the thickeſt,
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:106022:53"/>flew ſo abundantly about his Ears, that his Eyes were quite blinded; and not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſatisfied with this Revenge, I flew at his Hair and Face as if <hi>I</hi> had been ſome infernal Fury, while he was endeavouring to clear his Eyes that were all beſmeared with T—d, and <hi>I</hi> imprinted my Nails ſo deeply in him, that <hi>Don Quixot</hi> was never more hideous to ſee when he had that famous Battel with the Cats in the <hi>Dukes</hi> Houſe. <hi>I</hi> was alſo tranſported with ſuch a Rage (for, as they ſay, a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man in Anger is worſe than the Devil) that <hi>I</hi> ſhould have render'd him incapable of ever having the uſe of his Sight, if the honeſt Gentleman, who, without open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Mouth, unleſs it were to laugh, had all this while been Spectator of this Buſtle, had not pull'd me from him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Maximus</hi> had no ſooner got looſe from me, than that he was thinking to get Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction for this Affront: But his Eyes not being well enough open, he ran ſo blindly againſt a Chair that ſtood near the Chimney, that he fell head-long into the Fire, wherein he burnt the Curles <hi>I</hi> had left him; and if the honeſt Gentleman, who had already freed him once out of
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:106022:54"/>the Peril, had not come again to his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief, he had had his Face in the moſt mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable Condition imaginable. Ha, Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens! ſaid he, as ſoon as he was got on Foot again, ſhall it then be ſaid that <hi>I</hi> muſt endure ſo many Miſchiefs for a Curſed Whore? And then flouncing again upon me, he intended to have renewed the Battery, but he was repulſed by the other, who, after having twice freed him out of the Danger, that not only he would not give him more Relief, but that he would himſelf become his Adverſary.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Maximus</hi> thus perceiving there was no Revenge to be had at that time, went out of the Houſe, his Cloaths all covered with a Sirreverence, and his Head without Hair; but it was not without giving himſelf a thouſand times to the Devil, that he would make me pay dearly for the Pranck <hi>I</hi> had play'd him.</p>
            <p>In the mean while the Devil had an abſolute Protection over him: For before ten days were at an end, he ſent to beſeech me, like a perfect Fool and mad man, that he might have the happineſs of Drinking with me for the terminating
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:106022:54"/>our Quarrel. It ſeems he could not live without my Preſence; and that Love and Jealouſie were the Cauſe that he was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways quarrelling with me.</p>
            <p>I told the Perſon who had received the Commiſſion to come and make me this Compliment, that it was a Propoſition that I could not at all comply with, unleſs I might have abſolute Aſſurance of his good Will: For I had a Fancy that all this was done only to ſeek an Occaſion to do me a Miſchief. To make ſhort, we became afterwards good Friends, by the Mediation of this Embaſſador, and our Intrigue laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for a Year, during which, <hi>Maximus</hi> was very careful to frequent me: But at the end of that time marrying with a Widow our Familiarity was loſt by little and little. I ſay by little and little: For tho' he was married, he could not ſo well forget my Careſſes, but that he ſtill came to viſit me from time to time; but becauſe his Hands did not ſcatter Money with the ſame Liberality they did before; and that there were no more <hi>Indian</hi> Rarities for me to expect (for his Wife look'd after them too narrowly) my counterfeit Inclination did cool ſo much with time, that at length
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:106022:55"/>he ſtayed at home without returning any more to my Houſe.</p>
            <p>Now muſt I laugh at the fooliſhneſs of ſome men, whoſe unbounded Petulancy carries them ſometimes ſo far, that they will forget the moſt horrible Affronts, on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that they may not be baniſh'd from the Favor of a Woman, whoſe Careſſes they muſt purchaſe, while that another may as well as them enjoy her Affections for his Money. Without lying, thoſe men ſhew that their Bodies have an Empire over their Minds, and that they are only Men, becauſe they have the Figure of them: For is it not the greateſt Sillyneſs, and the higheſt Madneſs that can be commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that to ſatisfie the deſire of a little Bit of Fleſh, they proceed to the loſing their Eſtates, their Reputations, and all they have deareſt in the World, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergo, and forget all manner of Affronts; neither more nor leſs than if you were ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged to endure them. Nevertheleſs, it would be in ſome manner excuſable: For the Wiſeſt that have ever been upon Earth, ſuffer themſelves to be ſeduced by Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men; if theſe Sparks were aſſured of the Inclination of thoſe who coſt them ſo
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:106022:55"/>much Money, and who make them ſuffer ſo much without their growing impati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent.</p>
            <p>But to act in that manner with thoſe Nymphs, who, like Hackney Horſes are ready to ſerve every one, methinks, that ſince men have received ſo much Prudence, that it is a Shame for them to be led away to ſuch Extravagancies. True it is, that <hi>Maximus</hi> had no great reaſon to treat me in that manner: But however I fancy, that he was ſtill more to blame to court my Amity after I had uſed him ſo ſcurvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the preſence of another. Methinks that Shame alone ought to have forbidden him to have ever any Thoughts of me, unleſs he had a deſire to ſhew that he had a Reſentment for thoſe Affronts. But there are thoſe who are yet more ſilly: For I have ſeen thoſe, who without ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving given any Occaſion, ſuffered them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be aſhamed and affronted a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand times a day, without however think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of drawing the Foot out of the Snare, wherein their laſcivious Paſſion has made them fall. But I will engage no farther in this matter, that I may not deviate any farther from my Subject.</p>
            <pb n="108" facs="tcp:106022:56"/>
            <p>For two years time after that I had rid my ſelf of my <hi>Indian</hi> Merchant, I had ſo few Adventures of any Importance, that they do not deſerve I ſhould take the trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to deſcribe them; and to ſpeak the Truth, I had, during that time, ſo little Commerce in Gallantry, that I did not gain ſo much as I had done before: for by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that I ſtill became more and more ug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, I received no Benefit from any body, unleſs it were from thoſe whom I knew how to pleaſe by my Wit; but conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that's no great harm in Gallantry, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially to the Citizens, where they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly deſire Corporal Beauty; and on the contrary ſide what was worſt, my Tricks began to become ſomething too well known, that I loſt one day one, and the next day another, which made me begin to think of the means of getting my Livelyhood after another manner, namely by ſome Merchandiſe, for which I had Opportunity enough, being pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided with a good Sum of Money. And I had alſo the leſs reaſon to be uneaſie, in that I had Annuities to live on, as I have ſaid in the firſt part; and that by Conſequence I might live conveniently without troubling my Head with any
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:106022:56"/>Trade. True it is, that I muſt have ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken Delight in a ſolitary ſort of Life, and muſt have retrenched my Expences which I had no great Inclination to do: On the contrary, I was ſo accuſtomed to a Libertine way of Living, and Pride had took ſuch deep Root in my Heart, that it was a hard matter for me reſolve to go after the Rate of a Shop-Keeper's Wife.</p>
            <p>While I was thus contriving what would be moſt convenient and moſt uſeful to undertake, I began to imagine, that I ſhould not do ill in ſetting up a Lace-ſhop, becauſe that it is a Trade that requires no great trouble, and which brings a great deal of Profit; and particularly if you have the convenience of buying your Lace at the beſt hand. This deſign having been firmly concluded on, I left my Houſe to the keeping of a Marryed Woman, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving taken with me a good Sum of Money, I went into <hi>Flanders</hi> and ſo to <hi>Bruxels,</hi> to furniſh my ſelf with all things neceſſary for the garniſhing a handſome Shop.</p>
            <pb n="110" facs="tcp:106022:57"/>
            <p>Amongſt other Paſſengers there was a <hi>German</hi> Lord, attended with two Footmen in rich Liveries. He had no ſooner caſt his eyes upon me, than that he imagined, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps, that my Face was as Beautiful, as Paint and <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Paper made it ſeem; and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently began to ſhow his inclination, and upon the firſt occaſion, he came and ſat on the ſide of me, and as he had made good Proviſion for eating and drinking, he would not ſuffer in the leaſt that I ſhould meddle with my own Victuals; for really though the <hi>Germans</hi> do not for the moſt part con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain a huge deal of Wit in their great Nod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dles, yet we muſt however give them this Commendation, that they ſhow themſelves much more Civil and Courteous towards Women, than many other Nations. His Civility made me immediately imagine, that ſome advantage might accrew to me from him; wherefore I us'd the Spark as amou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly as was poſſible.</p>
            <p>To make ſhort, before that we came to <hi>Newport,</hi> we agreed to ſpend a Night or two together at <hi>Antwerp,</hi> and to bring this to paſs, he had gently ſlipt into my Breaſt three or four Broad-pieces of Gold.</p>
            <pb n="111" facs="tcp:106022:57"/>
            <p>As ſoon as we were come to <hi>Antwerp</hi> we went to one of the moſt Conſiderable Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naries, where we Dined, and then we ask<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed if we might lie there for two or three Nights, and that we had occaſion for three Chambers at the leaſt; namely, one for us, another for the <hi>German</hi>'s Foot-men, and a third for my Maid. The Landlord expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting to gain a conſiderable Sum of Money upon this Occaſion, quickly cauſed all to be prepared we ſtood in need of, after which the Count and I took a turn to ſee the fine City of <hi>Antwerp,</hi> towards Evening we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned to our Inn, where my <hi>German</hi> who was a Brave Drinker, as are moſt of his Countrey-men, fell to drinking Bumpers ſo hard with ſome Sparks who were alſo lodg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed there, that he became as drunk as a Beaſt, and in that condition came he to Bed to me. Certainly if I had then been ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more given to Carnal Pleaſures, I ſhould have been ſomething vexed and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appointed, for with Drunken Men there may be a great deal of Wind, but it ſeldom Rains; but as the principal Queſtion was that of Money, I made no great Ceremony up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the point; yet ſince I make Profeſſion of having a ſincere heart in all things, I am willing to confeſs, that the Amorous
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:106022:58"/>Sport was not ſo unpleaſant to me, yet you muſt alſo know that I was not over-well pleaſed with all thoſe I had to do with, and that by Conſequence I could not find my Divertiſement with all manner of Gallants, for aſſure your ſelf when Miſſes endeavour to make Sparks believe, by their Counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit Motion, that they receive an unſpeaka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Pleaſure; this is not out of a good in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, but to oblige the Cavalier to do his Work the ſooner; and indeed, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out being of a Nature inſatiable in Laſcivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, a Woman cannot find ſatisfaction in the Embraces of a Man ſhe had never ſeen before.</p>
            <p>After we had been a pretty while in un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſing him, wherein I was alſo aſſiſted by his Men, we went to Bed, and I expected to have enjoyed a very peacable Repoſe. But things do not always go according as we promiſe our ſelves. Which you may ſee by my <hi>German,</hi> for though he was ſo beaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly drunk, yet he had not forgotten for what reaſon he had deſired to have me his Bed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fellow, and tho' I uſed all imaginable means to make him defer that buſineſs un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til the Morning, for I was never willing to have to do with drunken Men, he would
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:106022:58"/>not be prevailed with, inſomuch, that I was forced to prepare my ſelf for it, unleſs that I had a mind to loſe all I promiſed my ſelf to gain by the Bargain.</p>
            <p>Whereupon I put my ſelf into ſuch a Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture as I thought moſt ſuitable to undergo the management a long time, for I foreſaw he would be a long while doing his Work. But while we were thus buſily taken up in our Affair, for I did alſo my beſt to be ſo much the ſooner diſengaged from him; the jogling did ſo raiſe the Wine, the Meat, and all the <hi>German</hi> had eaten that Evening, that in a moment he Vomited upon my Face a pot full of Filth, and this Evacuation being followed by three or four more of the ſame nature, I began to fear that Night would have been the laſt of my Life; for being ſo weary that I could hardly draw my Breath, which perhaps made me open my Mouth ſomething too wide, there entred into my Throat ſuch a great quantity of that villain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſtuff, that I thought I had been ſtifled, and if I had not forced my Knight to quit the Saddle, I ſhould have been but in a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable Condition. Beſides, that villainous ſtuff ſtunk ſo horribly, that having been put altogether in a <hi>Granado,</hi> they would have
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:106022:59"/>obliged a Man of War to have yielded, though it had been mounted with four and twenty pieces of Canon.</p>
            <p>An other Inconvenience followed upon the Heels of this, for as I was buſy in clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing my Mouth, my Stomach received the Air of this inſupportable ſtink, ſo that I vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted all I had therein, with ſuch a Violence, that I began to bleed at the Noſe.</p>
            <p>In the mean while as I could not cry out I made ſuch a noiſe with my Hands againſt the Beds teaſter, that at length one of the Maids came up with a light, and ſeeing us in that poſture, ſhe ſet the Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle upon the Table and ran to tell her Miſtreſs that we had ſpoiled one of her beſt Beds; for which reaſon ſhe did not fail to make a terrible Noiſe; but this ſtorm was appeaſed in a moment becauſe the <hi>German</hi> who was very much aſhamed at this accident, and who was then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come ſomething more ſober, payed accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Tax ſhe ſet upon that he had ſpoyled.</p>
            <pb n="115" facs="tcp:106022:59"/>
            <p>In the mean time while they were pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring another Bed, and I put on one of my Landladyes Smocks, and my Spark of a <hi>German</hi> who was ſomething better furniſhed with fine Linnen than my ſelf, had clean Linnen took out of his Port-Mantle, for thoſe we had on could not be more Dirty nor more wet, tho' it had rain'd T—rds and Surreverences upon them with full Palefuls, and we had mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched naked in our ſhifts quite through it all.</p>
            <p>In the mean while the honeſt Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man drank a good quantity of Pump-wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and by this means the Fumes of the Wine which were already half evaporated by the vomiting, diſſipated themſelves ſo well by his vomiting, that it could hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly any longer be obſerved that he had been drunk, to which alſo his ſhame did much contribute he had of ſo Beaſtly an action. As for my part I remain'd peacebly ſitting, and was ſtudying of the means to make him pay for this diſorder, for tho' he asked me a thouſand pardons which I willingly gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him in appearance, I was loath to let him come off at ſo cheap a rate as to let him go ſcot-free.</p>
            <pb n="116" facs="tcp:106022:60"/>
            <p>A thouſand ſort of thoughts roll'd in my Head; but amongſt all, there was not one wherein I did not find either impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility or a too viſible affectation, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore none of thoſe means ſeem'd to me more proper than the firſt which came into my fancy, whereof I will give you an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate account.</p>
            <p>When that our ſecond Bed was made ready, and that the Count imagined that the peace was entirely concluded, we went to ſleep; which I could do with ſo much the more tranquility for that I ſaw there would be nothing to do until the depth of the night. However I, as I never knew what profoundly ſleeping was, I heard the <hi>German</hi> ſeveral times make water, for tho' he had ſo ſwinginly skinned the Fox there was ſtill in his Body humidity e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough remaining, to fill the Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber pot. It was about break of day when he was again awaked out of his ſleep, and he almoſt filled the Pot quite full, as I could eaſily perceive by the noiſe he made.</p>
            <pb n="117" facs="tcp:106022:60"/>
            <p>Methoughts it was then time to put my deſign in execution: Wherefore I preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to ſtart out as a Dream; ah my dear little Angel, ſaid I to him, I deſire you would give me the Pot a little, my dear heart, ſaid he to me, it is ſo full I know not if you can make uſe of it. Yes well enough, replyed I, my Bladder is not ſo great, and beſides I know not if I can make water. Then the poor Ninnyham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer took the Pot in both his Hands and gave it me, and ſtood till I had done, for by reaſon the Pot ſtood upon a Chair by the Bedſide, and that he lay on the ſame, expecting to ſet it in its place again, and indeed I was for above a quarter of an hour without letting fall a drop, tho' I ſtill made Faces as if I ſtrained hard; but when I perceived he was fallen again aſleep, I got me up and fell plump upon his Body, neither more nor leſs than if I had been in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tangled in the Bed-Cloaths, I overturned the Pot and ſo let all the Urine fall upon his Face. S'Blood and Death, ſaid the <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> as ſoon as he felt the weight of my Body and that innundation of unexpected rain, I believe that the Devil reigns in this Houſe, otherwiſe how ſhould one receive ſo many misfortunes in one night alone?
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:106022:61"/>Thereupon leaping with his naked Breech out of the Bed, he blaſphemed and made ſuch a noiſe as if the Man had been poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with a Devil. He call'd out for light. At the ſame time I jump'd alſo out of Bed, for in a moment he was ſo wet, that you could hardly find a dry place the bigneſs of a Pin's-head, and tho' I had the greateſt pain imaginable to contain my ſelf from laughing, I beſeech'd him in terms of Lamemation, that he would not attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute to me the fault thereof; that it was a miſchance; and that I was ready to do all that he pleaſed to give him Content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Done upon that Condition, ſaid the <hi>German,</hi> and moreover I cannot take it in ill part, tho' it had been done on pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, but yet I am willing to have a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Opinion of you.</p>
            <p>In the mean while the Landlady came up with a light grunting all the way, becauſe ſhe was not ſuffered to ſleep at reſt, and ſeeing this ſecond Bed was as well ſpoiled as the other. By my ſoul, ſaid ſhe, I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but believe that you are reſolved to make me mad to night: Ah my dear Land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lady, I conjure you to be ſilent, ſaid the <hi>German,</hi> who could hardly open his Eyes
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:106022:61"/>by reaſon of the ſharp humour of the Piſs, reckon only what is due for this dammage, and give us another Bed; I am reſolved to ſee if the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil will come and play his part too there.</p>
            <p>All this while I bit my Lips ſo hard that the blood was ready to guſh out, for as I ſaw the Piſs ſtill trick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling from his Hair into this poor Wretches Eyes, I was taken with ſo great a deſire to laugh, for I would willingly have given a Guinney or two to have eas'd and given that ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction to my Breaſt. Thus were we led again into another Chamber by the Woman, grumbling and ſcolding, after which the <hi>German</hi> put on another clean Shirt; thus did he ſhift himſelf three times that Night, which undoubtedly he never did before ſince he was Born.</p>
            <pb n="120" facs="tcp:106022:62"/>
            <p>After this diſaſtrous Night, we ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>journed two days longer in this Inn; but it was with more good luck, for afterwards there happened no Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chances to us.</p>
            <p>After which, my Honeſt <hi>German</hi> departed for <hi>Nechelen,</hi> where he ſaid he had ſome Affairs, and would ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry willingly have took me along to have accompanied him thither; but becauſe I was willing to think on my Concern, I gave him many thanks for his offer, and went my way to <hi>Bruxelles</hi> with my Maid, though per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps, I had not done ill, if I had gone along with him, for he was a Debonnaire Spark, and as Amiable and Courteous, as a Woman could deſire.</p>
            <p>We ſtaid about a Week at <hi>Bruxelles,</hi> as well to ſee the Town and Court, as to buy the things for which we came thither; I do not queſtion
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:106022:62"/>but that I might have made ſome Gains there, for New Fleſh is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly deſired, and ſought after; but the fear I was in that the poor <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Courtiers would not pay me according to my Merit, I thought I ſhould do better in ſparing my Glan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and beſtow them upon others who had wherewith to recompence me well, in caſe that Fortune was ſtill ſo favourable to me, that ſhe would addreſs ſome more of thoſe Sparks to me again. But whereas during my Youth, ſhe had been as a Mother in ſuch Encounters, ſhe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to become a Mother-in-Law to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards me; for ſince this Voyage into <hi>Brabant,</hi> I have had ſo few Occupa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, that one would have believed by ſeeing the cloſing of my <hi>Tuzzy-Muzzy,</hi> that I had recovered a new Maiden-head in my old days. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs, I might have found ſome few to whom I ſhould not have been ſo unacceptable, if I would have ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:106022:63"/>them to have made uſe of me for nothing; but that I could never be brought to, becauſe by that means I might have come to be deſpiſed; with ſo much the more reaſon as that I ſtood not in ſo much need of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney as to run the danger of loſing my health for a Crown or an Angel.</p>
            <p>As ſoon as I was returned from <hi>Flanders,</hi> with a ſufficient quantity of Laces, I caus'd the entrance of my Houſe to be prepared for the making a ſhop thereof, and not to live on that trade alone (for I knew not if I ſhould gain by it, and I was uſed to keep a good Table, I took a Miſs to lodge with me, who according to appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances, ſhould ſerve me in the Quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of a Shop Maid, though this was only to exerciſe with her the ſame Trade I had done before with my own Fleſh; and for that cauſe, for the drawing the more profit from thence, I inſtructed her with all thoſe
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:106022:63"/>things which a Lady of Pleaſure ought to know, for the heaping up a Sum of Money wherewith ſhe may maintain her ſelf during her Old Age. I acquainted her after what manner ſhe was to ſhow Affection to Men in Years; how ſhe was to comport her ſelf with the younger; what ſhe was to obſerve in the firſt Viſits; by what marks ſhe might judge if a Man was liberal or ſtingy.</p>
            <p>In ſhort, I imparted to her all thoſe Inſtructions that experience had taught me, and if my Leſſons were ſet down in Writing, I am ſure, that thoſe Women who could make due uſe of 'em would receive no ſmall profit by 'em; but becauſe I have no deſign to ſpur on others to do ill, I will rather bury them in an Eternal Silence, that I may not be accuſed of having led into a wrong way the Children of Perſons of Honour.</p>
            <pb n="124" facs="tcp:106022:64"/>
            <p>My deſign ſucceeded as well as I could have deſired, for my Shop ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved for a pretext to Gentlemens co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming into my Houſe, and all was ſo peaceably governed there, that my neareſt Neighbours hardly knew that I committed the leaſt thing that was not honeſt, becoming and Civil.</p>
            <p>This Commerce had laſted about four years without my receiving the leaſt Croſs or Traverſe, when I was taken with a fit of Sickneſs, which in a few days brought me to the brink of Death. As then in ſuch rencoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters people become ſomething wiſer than they uſed to be, and as the thoughts of Death makes us often make promiſes to him, whom one does not think of in ones Health, I alſo made Vows that if ever I reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered again, I would lead a better Life, and that I would abandon all the Means which I had thitherto made uſe of. I know not if my Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:106022:64"/>were heard, or if my Sickneſs was come to its terme, yet by degrees I returned to my former Condition; the truth is, I put the Miſs out of the Houſe as I had made a Vow to doe, and that after this time I have never had any other of the ſame Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition; but yet I muſt confeſs by reaſon I will not have the reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of having ever been a Diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bler, that the Fleſh has been ſome times ſtronger than the Spirit; ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs I have at laſt gain'd the Victory over that Enemy, or if you will have it ſo, Years have rendred me ſo ugly, that no Body now comes to torment me any more for ſuch like things. However I do not ſpeak after this manner, but that infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly I ſhall not be believed if I would paſs for a Vertuous Perſon, which might be contradicted by a certaine place of this ſecond part, as alſo by my way of writing which is ſomething bold and libertine;
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:106022:65"/>but I content my ſelf with the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony that my Conſcience gives me, and it is the ſame-thing to me whether I am thought diſcreet, ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous or debaucht; becauſe that I have Experience enough in the World to know that it often blames Wiſe and Sober Perſons, and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten praiſes and extols ſuch as are lewd and vicious. Nevertheleſs I am not of the rank of thoſe who after having led a vicious Life du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring their Youth, and then beco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming Converts, pretend to by got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, and walk holding their right-Hand upon their Heart as the tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Devout do, or, if you pleaſe, ſeem as modeſt and as plain as poor <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſanna</hi> is commonly painted between thoſe two old Ruffions. On the contrary I am like to thoſe old Coach-men who can willingly hear the ſound of the Whip, with ſo much the more reaſon, as that it ſeems rather a folly than a probi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:106022:65"/>to forbid Men Joy and Mirth, by ſad and Melancholly Grimaces. It is a priviledge that we have pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferably to all other Creatures, and for that reaſon I have done it as of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten as things required, and I do not believe that I can deſiſt from it tho' a number of curious Fools ſhould tax me with being a Perſon of ill Conduct, until that Death has clos'd up my Mouth.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:106022:66"/>
            <head>Books Printed for <hi>H. Rodes</hi> next the Bear Tavern near <hi>Bride-lane</hi> in <hi>Fleet-ſtreet.</hi>
            </head>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>THe Strange and Prodigious Religions, Cuſtoms, and Manners of ſundry Nations.</hi> Containing, Firſt, The ridiculous Rites and Ceremonies of the <hi>Heathens</hi> in the Worſhip of their ſeveral Deities. Secondly, The various changes of the <hi>Jewiſh Religion,</hi> and the ſtate it is now in; with a full Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of the Apparitions that foretold the fall of <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> as alſo of the dreadful Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min, wherein a Woman roaſted and eat her own Child, with all the Cicumſtances of the final Deſtruction of that Famous City under <hi>Titus.</hi> Thirdly, The Riſe and Growth of Mahometaniſm, giving an account of the Doctrine of the <hi>Turkiſh Alcoran;</hi> viz. their Commandments, and their ſtrange Pilgrimage to <hi>Mecca,</hi> &amp;c. with the Life of that Crand Impoſtor <hi>Mahomet.</hi> As alſo, Remarks on the Life of <hi>Scanderbeg,</hi> with the many Victories he gained over the <hi>Turks.</hi> Fourthly, the Schiſms and Hereſies in the Chriſtian Church; being an account of the Blaſphemies of thoſe grand Hereticks
<pb facs="tcp:106022:66"/>the <hi>Adamites, Muggletonians,</hi> &amp;c. and all intermingled with pleaſant Relations of the Fantaſtical Rites both of the Ancients and Moderns in the Celebration of their Marria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges and Solemnization of their Funerals, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Faithfully collected from Antient and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dern Authors; and adorned with divers Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures of ſeveral remarkable Paſſages therein. By <hi>R. D.</hi> Price bound one ſhilling.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>The Hiſtory of the Glorious Life, Reign, and Death of the Illuſtrious</hi> Queen Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth. Containing an Account by what Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods the Reformation of the Church of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland</hi> were promoted and eſtabliſhed; and what Obſtructions it met with. The many Propoſitions of ſeveral great Princes to marry her, and her An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers to them: with a perfect Relation of the ſeveral horrible Attempts of the Papiſts againſt the Sacred Life of her Majeſty, by Conſpiracies, Rebellions, Aſſaſſinates, and poiſoning. The whole Affair of the Queen of <hi>Scots,</hi> the ſeveral Commotions of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Scotland, Ireland, France,</hi> and the <hi>Low Countries,</hi> during her Reign. Sir <hi>Francis Drake</hi>'s Voyage round the world, with his ſeveral Expeditions into <hi>America.</hi> Her ai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and aſſiſting the Proteſtants of <hi>France</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:106022:67"/>and the <hi>Low Countries.</hi> Her Alliances with ſeveral Proteſtant Princes, The Defeat of the, ſo called, <hi>Invincible Armado,</hi> in Eighty Eight; The taking and burning of <hi>Cadiz,</hi> by the <hi>Engliſh;</hi> with all the other remarkable Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currences of that Time, By <hi>S. Clark.</hi> The ſecond Edition Corrected, to which is now added, an Account of the many Troubles ſhe ſuffered before ſhe came to the Crown. Illuſtrated with Pictures of ſome conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable matters; curiouſly ingraven on Copper Plates. Price 1 s.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:106022:67"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
